<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Sanyam Khurana</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/</link><description>Curious Learner | FOSS Contributor | Passionate Geek</description><atom:link href="feeds/feeds/foss.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 17:11:00 +0530</lastBuildDate><item><title>MozAMU: Mozilla Addons Development at AMU</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/mozilla-addons-dev-amu.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;It all started with PyCon India. I met a few students of Aligarh Muslim University who were trying to teach about FOSS in their college. A few them were already contributing to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/coala/coala"&gt;Coala&lt;/a&gt;. We talked a bit and they were discussing problems they were facing to run that community. I already started a Mozilla community at my college in the earlier days. Since I brought up a lot of folks from my college community in the event, we together discussed &lt;em&gt;How to nurture FOSS communities in college&lt;/em&gt; as part of PyCon India Open Spaces. Here is a glimpse of the same:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="PyCon India Open Spaces on how to nurture FOSS communities in college" class="align-center" src="images/moz-addons-amu-1.jpeg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later, these folks were excited and invited me as a speaker at their college. A lot of planning happened for the event and we were in daily touch almost daily for different things. We planned the event one and a half month in advance. Finally, on 24th Feb 2018, we decided to have a full-day event around FOSS at Aligarh Muslim University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We left from Delhi at around 6:30 AM in the morning. We then halted at a cafe known as &lt;cite&gt;Break Point&lt;/cite&gt; around Aligarh to have breakfast. We reached the university at around 10:20 AM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We took some time to test the entire set-up and the event began at around 11:30 AM. I took the first session on &lt;strong&gt;Why you should contribute to Open Source&lt;/strong&gt;. We discussed the question that somehow pops up sooner or later into everyone's mind while contributing to Open Source: &lt;strong&gt;What's in it for me?&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We discussed various pathways one can begin contributing to Open Source Projects like &lt;strong&gt;coding, writing docs, managing team, advocacy, documentation, translation, bug triaging, reviews, organization skills, soft skills&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;amp; tons of other things that come as a by-product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Curious &amp;amp; enthusiastic attendees learning about different contribution pathways in FOSS" class="align-center" src="images/moz-addons-amu-9.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the slides here: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sanyamkhurana.com/presentations/why-foss"&gt;Why you should contribute to Open Source?&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Curious &amp;amp; enthusiastic attendees at Mozilla AMU" class="align-center" src="images/moz-addons-amu-2.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had a break for sometime and then started with the much awaited &lt;strong&gt;Add-ons session&lt;/strong&gt;. Everyone was very excited to start learning to develop add-ons. I began with explaining the initial setup details &amp;amp; discussed JSON briefly to bring everyone on the same page. To make most out of the event, We also organized a few events previously to teach basics of JavaScript &amp;amp; JSON so that students so that they do not feel overwhelmed with the add-ons development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Curious &amp;amp; enthusiastic attendees learning from Sanyam Khurana (CuriousLearner)" class="align-center" src="images/moz-addons-amu-3.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then Shashank (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://github.com/realslimshanky"&gt;&amp;#64;realslimshanky&lt;/a&gt;) took over and discussed &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;manifest.json&lt;/tt&gt; and it's importance. Later we developed a simple addon -- borderify, which displays a border on every site the user visits. Some students also modified their scripts to make their add-ons do different things and posted them on twitter. Shashank, me and Shivam Singhal (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://github.com/championshuttler"&gt;&amp;#64;championshuttler&lt;/a&gt;) helped everyone with their problems during the development phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Curious &amp;amp; enthusiastic attendees learning from Sanyam Khurana (CuriousLearner)" class="align-center" src="images/moz-addons-amu-4.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since all of us are devs, we were able to quickly resolve queries of students. One of the most important things I noticed is that often people misspell either the name of their manifest file or some key in their manifest people resulting their add-on to not load during the debugging phase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of them then created addons on their own and modified their previously created borderify addon to do more stuff. I've tried to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://gist.github.com/CuriousLearner/1a4b08dbf642be8e4dfeb9544c9ab4c9"&gt;collect some of them here&lt;/a&gt;. For a more verbose list you can visit Twitter and search tweets tagging me (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://twitter.com/ErSanyamKhurana"&gt;&amp;#64;ErSanyamKhurana&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23MozAMU"&gt;#MozAMU&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imaginations ran wild and one of the attendee created an addon that replaces the world &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Google&lt;/tt&gt; with &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Mozilla&lt;/tt&gt; on every web page. You can see &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/husainhz7/GoogleMozilla/"&gt;his hack here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To make the session more interesting we gave add-ons stickers to anyone who answers the question about what we were just telling them. A lot of folks praised and tweeted about the addons they were generating. We were able to generate &lt;strong&gt;10,000+ impressions with more than 4,000+ accounts reached on Twitter for #MozAMU&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Twitter Outreach report on no of impressions created for #MozAMU" class="align-center" src="images/moz-addons-amu-11.png" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Twitter Outreach report on top contributors created for #MozAMU" class="align-center" src="images/moz-addons-amu-12.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://tweetreach.com/reports/20714737"&gt;read the full report here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Till this time, I never introduced to anyone about who am I and most importantly not listed any of my contributions in any of the projects. I don't want them to feel overwhelmed and assume that we people have some sort of superpowers that we're able to patch bugs in any FOSS project. I always make it a point to encourage them and help them land their first patch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And my introduction summed that up in just one line &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;I'm one of you &lt;span class="pre"&gt;--&lt;/span&gt; a part of the community&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Sanyam Khurana (CuriousLearner) teaching about essential things to learn while contributing to FOSS projects" class="align-center" src="images/moz-addons-amu-13.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then hopped on to discuss &lt;strong&gt;How do I start contributing to Open Source?&lt;/strong&gt; where we specifically discussed &lt;strong&gt;How to find bugs on different projects through Bugzilla &amp;amp; Bugsahoy&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Enthusiastic folks learning about contributions for Sanyam Khurana (CuriousLearner)" class="align-center" src="images/moz-addons-amu-7.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sanyamkhurana.com/presentations/foss/#/"&gt;slides here&lt;/a&gt;. Then I discussed other Open Source projects I've contributed to like &lt;em&gt;CPython, Django, Oppia, Mozilla's Devtools, Gecko-Engine &amp;amp; tried to find out similarities in various bug trackers.&lt;/em&gt; We then had a group photo with some of the attendees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Group photo at Mozilla AMU" class="align-center" src="images/moz-addons-amu-5.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was already 5 PM and we didn't go for Lunch since students kept us busy with their questions during the lunch break too :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Curious &amp;amp; enthusiastic students asking questions in break" class="align-center" src="images/moz-addons-amu-8.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we decided to hop-on to a restaurant nearby with the core-team of students that helped in organizing the event with so much enthusiasm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Curious &amp;amp; enthusiastic attendees at Mozilla AMU" class="align-center" src="images/moz-addons-amu-10.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we clicked one last photo before leaving Aligarh at around 7:00 PM with the core-volunteers of the event who helped in all the preparations for the event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Group photo Mozilla AMU" class="align-center" src="images/moz-addons-amu-6.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I would like to congratulate the students for making so wonderful arrangements and pushing up the FOSS community in their college. I hope they will now start landing patches in different FOSS projects &amp;amp; we'll all meet again soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 17:11:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2018-03-01:blog/mozilla-addons-dev-amu.html</guid><category>foss</category><category>remo</category></item><item><title>Web Extensions, Womoz &amp; Privacy</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/web-extensions-womoz-privacy.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;A Saturday well spent teaching students about Open Source, Add-ons and Privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had an activity at Indira Gandhi Delhi Technical University for Women (IGDTUW)
for Addons, WoMoz and Privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session started with Trishul giving a talk on getting started with Add-ons.
He explained about Web Extensions and how they are useful. He also depicted some
of the extensions built by the community. He explained the use of &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;manifest&lt;/tt&gt;
file and then students started making simple add-ons on their own. The
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/Add-ons/WebExtensions/Your_first_WebExtension"&gt;borderify&lt;/a&gt;
Web Extension was chosen to teach students. Me, Trishul and Shivam helped them
whenever they were stuck.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Web Extension session" src="images/moz-addons.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next session was took by Faye on Women in Mozilla and how we can improve the
no of women contributors in the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Faye engaging participants" src="images/moz-addons-faye.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The third session was took by me where I discussed about &lt;cite&gt;What is FOSS&lt;/cite&gt; and why
people should contribute to FOSS. We then discussed on various pathways one can
start contributing. We also discussed on finding bugs through BugZilla and Bugsahoy
for Mozilla.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then Shashikanth discussed about importance of Privacy issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We ended the event with a capture of all enthusiastic faces in the meetup:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Group photo after Mozilla Web Extension session" src="images/moz-addons-group.jpg" /&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 23 Jan 2018 20:15:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2018-01-23:blog/web-extensions-womoz-privacy.html</guid><category>mozilla</category><category>remo</category></item><item><title>Moz-Fedora Day</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/moz-fedora-day.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;We recently organized Moz-Fedora Day, a one day event on promoting FOSS through
Mozilla &amp;amp; Fedora at Investopad, Hauz Khas, Delhi on Jan 13, 2018. The aim was
to depict the usage of packaging &amp;amp; building one of the Mozilla's project using Fedora.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Sanyam explaining about Mozilla &amp;amp; it's mission" src="images/moz-fedora-day-4.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The core event focused on making the participants automate the build of any of
the Mozilla's open source project of their choice. The aim is to influence
people to switch to Linux as a build environment (We used Fedora for this)
and introduce the basics of the version control system (Mercurial in case of Mozilla).
The event will also introduce to Vagrant for running standardized virtual
machines for build environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Sanyam engaging participants on Moz-Fedora Day" src="images/moz-fedora-day-3.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session began with Saurabh representing a bit about Fedora and other Linux
Distributions. I discussed about Mozilla, it's mission and different projects.
We then decided to package &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://servo.org/"&gt;Servo&lt;/a&gt; in Fedora and guided
folks through the steps to build the system. We used simple Vagrant setup to
package Servo project with Fedora.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Sanyam explaining about build systems" src="images/moz-fedora-day-2.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the event, we had a small discussion on how one can find bugs
through Bugzilla &amp;amp; Bugsahoy. The presentation can be found here:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sanyamkhurana.com/presentations/foss/"&gt;http://www.sanyamkhurana.com/presentations/foss/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also distributed some swags to folks who were able to make builds successfully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Swag Distribution" src="images/moz-fedora-day-1.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of this was a hands-on session and I saw new faces who were truly excited to
learn about these things. A Saturday well spent, spreading the love of Open Source.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 14 Jan 2018 20:15:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2018-01-14:blog/moz-fedora-day.html</guid><category>mozilla</category><category>remo</category></item><item><title>Ending the year with MozCoffee</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/mozcoffee-2017-end.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;We had &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;MozCoffee Delhi&lt;/tt&gt; on last Saturday, Dec 23, 2017. We had a lot of Rep
Attendees this time with other Mozillians. What would have been a better way to
end an year than the MozCoffee. From past various months, the activities in
Mozilla Delhi came to a stand still. But then we had MozCoffee planned in less
than a week. Thanks to my new mentor Trishul for arranging MozCoffee at Chaayos,
Connaught Place, New Delhi on 23rd December, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We gathered up at the venue in the evening and met a lot of new and old people.
We had Trishul, Faye, Sanyam, Tanzeel, Dvyik, Rajiv, Saurabh, Pushpita, Shivam, Tushar at the meetup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discussion started with Trishul explaining about his experience in All Hands Austin.
He told about various projects that have been identified by Mozilla as the major
areas of contributions. We discussed about both tech &amp;amp; non-tech contributions
in various areas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Near the end of the event, Trishul also helped me in explaining about addons.
Since I've previous experience with JS, it was pretty easy to pick that stuff up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, we had some amazing photographs which would now become a memory for all of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="MozCoffee" src="images/mozcoffee-2017-end-1.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="MozCoffee" src="images/mozcoffee-2017-end-2.jpg" /&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 24 Dec 2017 20:34:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2017-12-24:blog/mozcoffee-2017-end.html</guid><category>remo</category><category>mozilla</category></item><item><title>Promoted to bug-triager for CPython</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/cpython-promotion.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This is huge! I couldn't believe when I just woke up next to this mail:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Sanyam Khurana has been promoted" src="images/cpython_bug_triage.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, I got promoted to &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Developer&lt;/tt&gt; role on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bugs.python.org"&gt;bugs.python.org&lt;/a&gt;, which along with other privileges, provides access to close bugs. But with great powers, comes great responsibilities. Closing bugs means that the information is lost forever. So, utmost care is to be taken and reported on why a bug is closed (which might even involve writing code/scripts that prove it :)).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Victor Stinner is mentoring me and a few other folks who have been promoted to learn more about contributing to CPython code base. I've been reading the dev-guide and understanding the entire process to be followed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently we've been also practicing to review Pull Requests along with reporting bugs and contributing code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope to learn more about the process and contribute more to CPython. I wanted to write this post to specially thank &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://kushaldas.in"&gt;Kushal Das&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/ncoghlan"&gt;Nick Coghlan&lt;/a&gt; who helped me getting started with CPython in Feb 2017 during &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pune.pycon.org"&gt;PyCon Pune&lt;/a&gt; sprints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, thanks to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/vstinner"&gt;Victor Stinner&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/ezio-melotti"&gt;Ezio Melotti&lt;/a&gt; for providing me those privileges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope to get a better understanding of the code base and contribute more ;)&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2017 20:34:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2017-12-20:blog/cpython-promotion.html</guid><category>foss</category><category>python</category><category>cpython</category></item><item><title>The cycle of creating bugs and patching them</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/cpython-contribution-print-enhancement.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I write patches, which creates more bugs; then I go and patch them again. The cycle continues...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you've been following up my recent contributions on the CPython code-base, sometime back I added an enhancement patch to the code-base which presents the user a suggestion on the correct syntax hint for calling built-in &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;print&lt;/tt&gt; function in Python 3.6 &amp;amp; 3.7 if it is used as an old style &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;print&lt;/tt&gt; statement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently a &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugs.python.org/issue32028"&gt;bug was filed&lt;/a&gt; for that new feature. I am more than excited to hear this news (because people have already started using the feature I added to Python programming language :))&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
When the following code is executed by Python 3.6.3 inside of a &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;.py&lt;/tt&gt; file:&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;f&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;():&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;%d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;then&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Python&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;gives&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;following&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;error&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;message&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="ne"&gt;SyntaxError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Missing&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;parentheses&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;call&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;print&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Did&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;you&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;mean&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nb"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="si"&gt;%d&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;%&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;?&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the issue with the earlier patch was this as Nick suggested:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Given the symptoms (stripping 4 spaces + &amp;quot;pr&amp;quot; from the start of the line, leaving &amp;quot;int &amp;quot; behind), it looks like we're not stripping the leading whitespace when determining the text to include in the suggested print() call.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I got some time to work on this, it took me just 5 mins to re-patch it for the first version of the patch. (That is the fastest I've done in any bug in CPython, probably because the earlier patch was written by me.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, after review, we also did a bit of refactoring to that patch. It was already approved a few weeks ago but still waiting to be merged. Here is the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/python/cpython/pull/4688/files"&gt;updated patch&lt;/a&gt; if you want to see.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2017 20:34:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2017-12-15:blog/cpython-contribution-print-enhancement.html</guid><category>foss</category><category>python</category><category>cpython</category></item><item><title>Improving class instantiation error message logic in Python 3.7</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/cpython-improve-error-message-logic-for-class-instantiation.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Many folks ask me why I contribute to CPython. I think it is a special feeling which cannot be expressed in words. Even if you just fix a typo in the doc, believe me, you've actually helped a lot of developers and companies all over the world. Your (small) changes matters a lot. They make huge impact in FOSS world :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While browsing through bugs on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugs.python.org"&gt;bugs.python.org&lt;/a&gt; , I found a bug reported by a teacher who requested to enhance the error message logic as he described in one of the blog posts on his blog on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://blog.lerner.co.il/favorite-terrible-python-error-message/"&gt;Favorite Terrible Python Error Message&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;object_new&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;object_init&lt;/tt&gt; currently have &amp;quot;object&amp;quot; hardcoded in the error messages they raise for excess parameters. It is thus difficult for anyone facing that error to know what is going on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nick explained really well about the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugs.python.org/issue31506#msg302439"&gt;comment in the bug&lt;/a&gt; which I'm stating here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;C&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;pass&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;C&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Traceback&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;most&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;recent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;call&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;last&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;File&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;lt;stdin&amp;gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;module&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="ne"&gt;TypeError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;object&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;takes&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;no&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;parameters&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;c&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;C&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;c&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;__init__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Traceback&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;most&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;recent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;call&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;last&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;File&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;lt;stdin&amp;gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;module&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="ne"&gt;TypeError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;object&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;__init__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;takes&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;no&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;parameters&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="n"&gt;This&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;hardcoding&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;makes&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sense&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;case&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;where&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;that&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;particular&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;method&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;has&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;been&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;overridden&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;interpreter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;is&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;reporting&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;an&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;error&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;subclass&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;s call up to the base class, rather than in the call to create an instance of the subclass:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nc"&gt;D&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;     &lt;span class="k"&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nf"&gt;__init__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="bp"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;args&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;         &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;super&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;__init__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;args&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;...&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;D&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;10&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Traceback&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;most&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;recent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;call&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;last&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;File&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;lt;stdin&amp;gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;module&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;File&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;lt;stdin&amp;gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;__init__&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="ne"&gt;TypeError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;object&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;__init__&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;takes&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;no&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;parameters&lt;/span&gt;


&lt;span class="n"&gt;However&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;it&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;s misleading in the case where object_new is reporting an error because it knows object_init hasn&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;been&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;overridden&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="ow"&gt;or&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;vice&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;versa&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;),&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;hence&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;won&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;t correctly accept any additional arguments: in those cases, it would be far more useful to report &amp;quot;type-&amp;gt;tp_name&amp;quot; in the error message, rather than hardcoding &amp;quot;object&amp;quot;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thus started working on the patch to detect the cases when &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;excess_args&lt;/tt&gt; are supplied and show the correct error message.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now the error messages in &lt;cite&gt;object.__new__&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;object.__init__&lt;/cite&gt; aim
to point the user more directly at the name of the class being instantiated
in cases where they &lt;em&gt;haven't&lt;/em&gt; been overridden (on the assumption that
the actual problem is a missing &lt;cite&gt;__new__&lt;/cite&gt; or &lt;cite&gt;__init__&lt;/cite&gt; definition in the
class body).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When they &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; been overridden, the errors still report themselves as
coming from the object, on the assumption that the problem is with the call
up to the base class in the method implementation, rather than with the
way the constructor is being called.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're interested, you can see the whole &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/python/cpython/commit/780acc89bccf9999332d334a27887684cc942eb6"&gt;patch here&lt;/a&gt;.
I hope this patch would help all those kids and all the new and old folks playing with Python to learn about how objects are created and instantiated. It always feels great to make (small) changes. Helping in improving Python one patch at a time :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2017 20:34:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2017-12-11:blog/cpython-improve-error-message-logic-for-class-instantiation.html</guid><category>foss</category><category>python</category><category>cpython</category></item><item><title>Fixing the print redirection suggestion in Python 3.7</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/cpython-print-redirection-syntax-suggestion.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;If you've been following my contributions to CPython, I recently contributed an enhancement patch to &lt;cite&gt;Python 3.7&lt;/cite&gt; about &lt;a class="reference external" href="contributing-cpython-enhancement.html"&gt;producing correct suggestion for built-in print function in Python 3 if the old print 2 statement style is used&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The patch also got back-ported to &lt;cite&gt;Python 3.6&lt;/cite&gt; and is now available to you folks :) Continuing the development on this new suggestion hint, the next target was to produce the correct hint if anyone uses the old Python 2 redirection syntax like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;sys&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sys&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;stderr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;message&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here we're trying to redirect the &amp;quot;message&amp;quot; string on the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Standard Error&lt;/tt&gt; stream in Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The current error thrown is a &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;TypeError&lt;/tt&gt; like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="ne"&gt;TypeError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;unsupported&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;operand&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;type&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;builtin_function_or_method&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;_io.TextIOWrapper&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also wanted to display the correct syntax in Python 3 like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;sys&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;message&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;file&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;sys&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;stderr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was working on the patch, we realized that till the time the check is made to throw the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;TypeError&lt;/tt&gt; inside the interpreter, we don't have the relevant information about data passed with the print statement available. So, we decided to throw a generic suggestion which would be a constant expression not depending upon the input from the user.  But it would be good enough to suggest some meaningful modification the user could do to fix the error.  We ended up with the following suggestion hint:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kn"&gt;import&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nn"&gt;sys&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;sys&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;stderr&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;message&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Traceback&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;most&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;recent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;call&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;last&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;):&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;File&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;lt;stdin&amp;gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;module&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="ne"&gt;TypeError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;unsupported&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;operand&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;type&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;for&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;builtin_function_or_method&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;_io.TextIOWrapper&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Did&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;you&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;mean&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;print(&amp;lt;message&amp;gt;, file=&amp;lt;output_stream&amp;gt;)&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;?&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also included some test cases to verify the new feature. &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/python/cpython/commit/5e2eb35bbed3e84079165e576cdb50ef36e13493"&gt;Here is the full patch&lt;/a&gt; if you want to see. The meaning of each of the methods used can be easily found from the official documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope to write about my learning in more detail and also explain about different parts of the programming language in one of the future post.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 20 Aug 2017 20:34:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2017-08-20:blog/cpython-print-redirection-syntax-suggestion.html</guid><category>foss</category><category>python</category><category>cpython</category></item><item><title>Why you should contribute to Open Source</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/why-contribute-to-foss.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;My first step with FOSS was &lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/how-dgplug-training-is-proving-beneficial-to-me.html"&gt;during the summer of 2014&lt;/a&gt;, where I got introduced to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dgplug.org"&gt;DGPLUG&lt;/a&gt; (Durgapur Linux Users Group). Every year, they conduct a training over IRC covering a wide range of topics. Since then, I've been contributing to different projects, primarily to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/mozilla/gecko-dev"&gt;Mozilla's Gecko Engine&lt;/a&gt;. Recently I also started &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/python/cpython/pulls?utf8=%E2%9C%93&amp;amp;q=is%3Apr%20author%3ACuriousLearner"&gt;contributing to CPython&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/CuriousLearner/"&gt;this journey as CuriousLearner over the past few years&lt;/a&gt;, I've been fortunate enough to collaborate with some of the best engineers, learnt a lot of skills &amp;amp; gained some nice perspective on different technologies by just contributing to Open Source. I owe my learning to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been always asked this question by my friends, colleagues, and strangers whom I often run into in local meet-ups and conferences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why should I contribute to Open Source&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What's in it for me&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I thought I would cover this topic from the perspective of a student as well as the perspective of a working professional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="learn-new-skills"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Learn new skills&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I say skills, I'm not referring to just coding skills or learning yet another framework. There are tons of skills to be learnt. These include coding, debugging, testing, writing docs, collaboration, participating in meetings etc. In FOSS, you won't just learn technical skills, but soft skills as well. That means you'll learn how to communicate effectively over different mediums and making sense to other people who might be from different backgrounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've seen many engineers are hesitant when it comes to communication. They can think and write really nice code, but when it comes to explaining themselves, they lack the communication skills, which is vital to be a better professional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="improve-existing-skills"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Improve existing skills&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not always about learning a new tech that you heard about. It's important to improve on things you think &lt;em&gt;you might already know&lt;/em&gt;. Contributing to a FOSS project would make you learn intricate details that your mentors have gained working as a software craftsmen for several years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="meet-like-minded-people"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Meet like-minded people&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many organizations do stand-up / all-hands meetings where everyone comes together and explains what are they're working on, what they plan to do next and if they face any blocker. So, students, there is a high possibility that when you graduate, you'll do this in your organization :) You'll meet a lot of people having similar interests and you'll learn a lot of things just by hanging out with them (most of the time on IRC).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="learn-people-skills"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Learn people skills&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Learn team management, resolving internal conflicts, brainstorming on a new feature, public-speaking, time-management, conducting meet-ups &amp;amp; learn to prioritize your work. You will just expand your horizons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="learn-to-read"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Learn to READ&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the best things I've been ever taught is to &amp;quot;READ&amp;quot;. (And those who've met me personally knows how many times I've been repeating this thing :)).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I say read, I mean you'll read the documentation, development guide and most importantly the source code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Always remember that code is meant to be read more times than it is written. When you contribute to any FOSS project, one of the important skill you add to your skill-set is to make your brain make sense out of the code that may look gibberish to many people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a very important skill. Once you're in a company, you'll be given the responsibility of maintaining huge code base and constantly adding features to it. There won't be someone who would spoon-feed you by explaining what every line of code means.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've seen many people struggling hard in their jobs to figure out what a particular piece of code does. But if you've already worked with humongous code bases, this shall be a cake-walk for you. You would already know how to scrutinize bugs, debug errors and most importantly, would have already taught your brain to think and &lt;cite&gt;READ&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="find-mentors"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Find mentors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;FOSS is all about mentors &amp;amp; mentees. There are people just like me and you who volunteer their time and skill to do good for the community. You'll find a lot of mentors who would be willing to teach you different skills. Remember, that you've got this opportunity to learn from domain experts :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And no matter what, always respect everyone's time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="teach-others"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Teach others&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While it is important to get your code reviewed, it is much more important to review other's code. This would help you in learning different coding style and also about how someone approached a particular problem. This would help in expanding your logical skills &amp;amp; as always you'll be learning a lot yourself along the way with having healthy discussions in code reviews.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="it-feels-great-to-make-small-changes"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It feels great to make (small) changes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don't necessarily need to work on big features in a project or become a life-long contributor. Contribute to a project that you use on daily basis (like &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://whatcanidoformozilla.org/"&gt;Mozilla Firefox&lt;/a&gt;) and I promise you that it would be gratifying when you see the whole world rely on the small code changes you did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A small change in the documentation means you might save someone countless hours of debugging and scratching their head on how to use a particular piece of code. Always remember, documentation bugs are not something inferior; you'll learn a lot in writing documentation, right from the tools such as Sphinx and rST to expanding your domain knowledge about the project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="building-your-reputation-career-along-the-way"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Building your reputation (&amp;amp; career) along the way&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the code you'll write in Open Source projects would be public and can be taken as a demonstration of how you write code &amp;amp; what you can do. It depicts how you work with others and most importantly give you an enormous amount of experience in working with people having diversified skill-set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you get acquainted with the code base, you'll be invited to develop stand-alone features and who knows you might get that commit bit turned on when you've developed enough reputation in the community ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from all the things mentioned above, I think Mozilla's mission says a lot about why I contribute to FOSS&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Doing good is part of our code&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, I didn't realize, I'll be able to write this much. Hopefully, this would help &amp;amp; motivate people to get involved in contributing to Open Source. As always, if you have any queries, or want help in contributing to any project, feel free to mail me on &lt;strong&gt;Sanyam [at] SanyamKhurana [dot] com&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 26 Jun 2017 17:11:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2017-06-26:blog/why-contribute-to-foss.html</guid><category>foss</category><category>remo</category></item><item><title>Contributing enhancement patch to CPython</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/contributing-cpython-enhancement.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I started contributing to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/python/cpython"&gt;CPython&lt;/a&gt; this year from &lt;a class="reference external" href="/blog/pycon-pune-2017.html"&gt;PyCon Pune sprints&lt;/a&gt;. That was one of the best PyCon I've ever attended. Since then, I've spent some time in going through documentation, core dev-guide and now I'm still reading about internals of the Python programming language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently contributed an enhancement patch to Python 3.7 which might be back-ported to Python 3.6. Let's understand the scenario and the enhancement:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New contributor to Python 3 might use old Python 2 syntax treating &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;print&lt;/tt&gt; as a statement rather than a function and then see an error like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;hello&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;File&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;lt;stdin&amp;gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;hello&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="o"&gt;^&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="ne"&gt;SyntaxError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Missing&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;parentheses&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;call&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;print&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The task was to improve the error message based on different kinds of user input. This shall ensure that we don't only show error to the user but also suggest the correct syntax to be used as a hint. So after the patch being applied, the error message shall say this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;hello&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;File&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;lt;stdin&amp;gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;hello&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
                &lt;span class="o"&gt;^&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="ne"&gt;SyntaxError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Missing&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;parentheses&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;call&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;print&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Did&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;you&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;mean&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;hello&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;?&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sounds easy? Right? No, we aren't done yet. This was a simple print statement dealing with just a string. Potentially someone can try to print anything. What if someone wants to print a tuple?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;File&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;lt;stdin&amp;gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
          &lt;span class="o"&gt;^&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="ne"&gt;SyntaxError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Missing&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;parentheses&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;call&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;print&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Did&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;you&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;mean&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot; &amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;?&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the correct syntax is suggested to the user according to Python3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along with this, there are cases when someone adds soft-spaces, or just use excessive whitespace like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;hello&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="n"&gt;File&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;lt;stdin&amp;gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;line&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;    &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;hello&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
                   &lt;span class="o"&gt;^&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="ne"&gt;SyntaxError&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Missing&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;parentheses&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="ow"&gt;in&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;call&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;#39;print&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Did&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;you&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;mean&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="k"&gt;print&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;hello&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;?&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the first patch where I had to deal with C code. It was more of reading and understanding what the current code does. I had to do a complete re-write of this patch two times in a span of just 1.5 days (Thanks to Nick and Serhiy for the quick reviews).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's why:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first time I wrote the patch, I used raw C APIs, which means I used &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;malloc&lt;/tt&gt; and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;free&lt;/tt&gt; for memory allocation and deallocation for manipulating the string input that was received from the user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While this might work, but there is already a lot of work done by Python core-devs &amp;amp; they've created an entire &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://docs.python.org/3/c-api/"&gt;C API layer&lt;/a&gt;. So, in the first review, I was pointed to use this API layer, so I had to re-write the patch. One of the learning I had is that virtually any API can fail. So, it is necessary to always check the results before using them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the methods from the C-API layer that were used in this patch were dealing with &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://docs.python.org/3/c-api/unicode.html"&gt;Unicode objects&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another important learning was to deallocate the previous memory at each check point (if some of the API call fails and there is no memory allocated on heap then deallocate all the previous allocated memory).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apart from handling the striping of characters that were input on the shell and detecting the tuple syntax, I also wrote test cases for the new feature. In CPython, most of the test cases are written in Python (except a few). Typically in this use case, we only need to check the functionality of the Python layer, so test cases were written in Python.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's see how the added feature does what it is intended to do:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="c1"&gt;// Static helper for setting legacy print error message&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;static&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="nf"&gt;_set_legacy_print_statement_msg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;PySyntaxErrorObject&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;Py_ssize_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;start&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;PyObject&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;strip_sep_obj&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;PyUnicode_FromString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\t\r\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;strip_sep_obj&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;NULL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// PRINT_OFFSET is to remove `print ` word from the data.&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;PRINT_OFFSET&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;Py_ssize_t&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;text_len&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;PyUnicode_GET_LENGTH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;text&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;PyObject&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;data&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;PyUnicode_Substring&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;text&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;PRINT_OFFSET&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;text_len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;data&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;NULL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;Py_DECREF&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;strip_sep_obj&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;PyObject&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;new_data&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;_PyUnicode_XStrip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;strip_sep_obj&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;Py_DECREF&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;Py_DECREF&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;strip_sep_obj&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;new_data&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;NULL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="c1"&gt;// gets the modified text_len after stripping `print `&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;text_len&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;PyUnicode_GET_LENGTH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;new_data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;maybe_end_arg&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;text_len&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;PyUnicode_READ_CHAR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;new_data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;text_len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="sc"&gt;&amp;#39;,&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;maybe_end_arg&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot; end=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;PyObject&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;error_msg&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;PyUnicode_FromFormat&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;Missing parentheses in call to &amp;#39;print&amp;#39;. Did you mean print(%U%s)?&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="n"&gt;new_data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;maybe_end_arg&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;Py_DECREF&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;new_data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;error_msg&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;NULL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

    &lt;span class="n"&gt;Py_XSETREF&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;msg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;error_msg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This function returns the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 if the error message is successfully set.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;-1 in case any of the C-API fails.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, first we use &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;strip_sep_obj&lt;/tt&gt; to define all the symbols that we need to strip from the input received from the user. Next, when we get the string, it would be of the form &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;print &amp;quot;Hello&amp;quot;&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;PyObject&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;strip_sep_obj&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;PyUnicode_FromString&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\t\r\n&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;strip_sep_obj&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nb"&gt;NULL&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="k"&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="c1"&gt;// PRINT_OFFSET is to remove `print ` word from the data.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;PRINT_OFFSET&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we're interested in is about the text after the print and space. That accounts for the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PRINT_OFFSET&lt;/tt&gt; that is set to constant 6.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;_PyUnicode_XStrip&lt;/tt&gt; uses to strip &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;strip_sep_obj&lt;/tt&gt; from the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;data&lt;/tt&gt; we assigned earlier. The 2 in this function is a constant value that implies stripping the input from both sides of the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;data&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code c literal-block"&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;PyObject&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;new_data&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;_PyUnicode_XStrip&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;2&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;strip_sep_obj&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we get the length of the text and check if the input meant to print a tuple by checking the last character from the Unicode buffer to be equal to string literal &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;,&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code c literal-block"&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="kt"&gt;char&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;maybe_end_arg&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="k"&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;text_len&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="mi"&gt;0&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;&amp;amp;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;PyUnicode_READ_CHAR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;new_data&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;text_len&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="mi"&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;==&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="sc"&gt;','&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="n"&gt;maybe_end_arg&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="o"&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot; end=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="se"&gt;\&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s"&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After setting up the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;maybe_end_arg&lt;/tt&gt; we format the new message and use &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Py_XSETREF&lt;/tt&gt; to set the new &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;error_msg&lt;/tt&gt; to the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;PySyntaxErrorObject&lt;/tt&gt; instance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="code c literal-block"&gt;
&lt;span class="n"&gt;Py_XSETREF&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;self&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="n"&gt;msg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="n"&gt;error_msg&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/python/cpython/commit/3a7f03584ab75afbf5507970711c87042e423bb4"&gt;Here is the full patch&lt;/a&gt; if you want to see. The meaning of each of the methods used can be easily found from the official documentation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope to write about my learning in more detail and also explain about different parts of the programming language in a future post.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2017 20:34:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2017-06-20:blog/contributing-cpython-enhancement.html</guid><category>foss</category><category>python</category><category>cpython</category></item><item><title>Event Report - PyDelhi Conf 2017</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/pydelhi-conf-2017.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This was second year of PyDelhi Conf! It was a two day event organized at IIM-Lucknow, Noida Campus from March 18, 2017 to March 19, 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two day event covered various talks and workshops along with dev-sprints to help newbies to contribute to various Open Source projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also presented a talk at PyDelhi Conf on &lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;Building High Performance systems using Django&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;. The slides of the talk are available &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://SanyamKhurana.com/presentations/django-optimizations"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The major attraction in the event were a lot of panel discussions. One of the discussion was on increasing women participation in Open Source and appreciate the efforts of female contributors in computing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another panel discussion was on &amp;quot;OSS communities in Delhi: How we can possibly collaborate together&amp;quot;; where there were many Open Source contributors present from various communities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a group photo of all volunteers for PyDelhiConf:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Group Photo of volunteers for PyDelhi Conf" class="align-center" src="images/pydelhi-conf-2017-1.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find all the photos of the event on &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.flickr.com/photos/theskumar/sets/72157679909955640/"&gt;Flickr&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd like to congratulate every volunteer to come forward and help in conducting the conference. We're waiting excitingly to host PyCon India 2017 in Delhi!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2017 15:50:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2017-04-03:blog/pydelhi-conf-2017.html</guid><category>mozilla</category><category>foss</category></item><item><title>NIEC Activate Mozilla with WebVR</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/niec-mozilla-activate-webvr.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;On Saturday, January 28, 2017, we had an event planned at Northern India Engineering College on &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Activate Mozilla Campaign&lt;/tt&gt;. Our aim was to cover &lt;cite&gt;WebVR&lt;/cite&gt; track under &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Build the Web&lt;/tt&gt; activity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The event was scheduled from 12:00 PM IST to 4:00 PM IST.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I reached the venue at 10:40 AM and helped a bit with arrangements. Saturday was a day off for all college students, so honestly I didn't expect much audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, I was wrong. Students are more willing to learn and soon there were lot of students. In starting there were less people, but then we got a total audience of around 70+ which is huge considering that it was a holiday for them and they just came here to learn about FOSS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, out of the core-organizers, only Shivam was available. But we got support from other student volunteers to do various arrangements and co-ordinating all the sessions smoothly. I would take this opportunity to thank each one of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since, there were no other speakers, I had to take all the sessions. It began with an interactive session on what students understand by the term FOSS (Free &amp;amp; Open Source Software). I told about how Free Software and Open Source Software are same yet different from each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="NIEC Activate Mozilla" class="align-center" src="images/niec-moz-activate_1.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this we discussed about Mozilla and the Open Web. Since it was &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Data Privacy Day&lt;/tt&gt;, we also discussed about how important is privacy in the online world, yet most of us don't have proper information on it. We also discussed about &lt;cite&gt;Free Basics&lt;/cite&gt; and how various organizations keep track of our online identities; and how Mozilla as an organization is doing in protecting the Free Web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next session was on &lt;cite&gt;Introduction to Git &amp;amp; Github&lt;/cite&gt;. Although focus was on Activate Mozilla campaign, but I really wanted to teach about Version control to people considering that most people are Engineering students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Sanyam talking about Version Control using Git" class="align-center" src="images/niec-moz-activate_2.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Sanyam teaching about branching in version control systems" class="align-center" src="images/niec-moz-activate_3.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this we had a small break to let people grab the knowledge they just had. I was surprised by the enthusiasm of these students. In the break time too, many of them surrounded me with various questions like how to contribute to FOSS, how to start et. all. So, yes, it wasn't a break for me ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this session, we jumped on to Activate Mozilla Campaign. We told about various tracks under Activate Mozilla Campaign. The session was kick started with an introduction to Virtual Reality. We discussed about Visual and Input Immersion and how it is changing the Web as we use it today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this, we jumped on to learning A-Frame and making Virtual Reality scenes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Sanyam's talk on WebVR" class="align-center" src="images/niec-moz-activate_4.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Sanyam's talk on WebVR and A-Frame JS" class="align-center" src="images/niec-moz-activate_5.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="NIEC Activate Mozilla" class="align-center" src="images/niec-moz-activate_6.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="NIEC Activate Mozilla" class="align-center" src="images/niec-moz-activate_7.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we gave time to audience to try using A Frame to develop something. I will collect all those projects and post them here soon :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end we distributed swags to students.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="NIEC Activate Mozilla Swags" class="align-center" src="images/niec-moz-activate_8.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="NIEC Activate Mozilla" class="align-center" src="images/niec-moz-activate_9.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the event, we took feedback from people. Some of them are here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="NIEC Activate Mozilla Feedback" class="align-center" src="images/niec-moz-activate-feedback-1.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="NIEC Activate Mozilla Feedback" class="align-center" src="images/niec-moz-activate-feedback-2.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="NIEC Activate Mozilla Feedback" class="align-center" src="images/niec-moz-activate-feedback-3.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="NIEC Activate Mozilla Feedback" class="align-center" src="images/niec-moz-activate-feedback-4.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Out of these, I'm astonished to see, that 100% people want to learn more about it. One student wrote that he would really like if more simpler terms would be used. Surely, I would keep this in mind, and if someone told me this thing during the session, I would've helped them there itself. But I'd surely take care from next session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there is some MozLove on twitter as well :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="NIEC Activate Mozilla Feedback Twitter" class="align-center" src="images/niec-moz-activate-twitter-1.png" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="NIEC Activate Mozilla Feedback Twitter" class="align-center" src="images/niec-moz-activate-twitter-2.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I'm flooded with a lot of mails from students who're willing to contribute to FOSS and requesting for guidance. I have started replying to some, and will be replying to all of them soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2017 12:08:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2017-01-29:blog/niec-mozilla-activate-webvr.html</guid><category>mozilla</category><category>remo</category><category>foss</category></item><item><title>Representing Mozilla in FOSS UnConference</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/mozilla-foss-unconference.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;On December 17, 2016; we had FOSS un-conference where all Open Source groups gathered to discuss about the FOSS culture. We had people from PyDelhi, PyData Delhi, Mozilla Delhi (MozPacers), LinuxChix India, Sympy, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had three talks scheduled:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Netfilters by Shyam Saini, Networking by Manpreet [:msn] &amp;amp; Deep learning by Shagun&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="FOSS unconference" class="align-center" src="images/foss-unconference_1.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="FOSS unconference" class="align-center" src="images/foss-unconference_2.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the talks, we had a panel discussion where there was representative from each community discussing about how each community works; what are the pros and cons in different Open source communities, how can we improve the participation to FOSS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="FOSS unconference" class="align-center" src="images/foss-unconference_3.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also discussed about women participants in different open source communities &amp;amp; also about increasing their participation in every community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="FOSS unconference" class="align-center" src="images/foss-unconference_4.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm also actively helping in reviving LinuxChix India which focuses on empowering women tech participation in Open source world. Hope to see some good participation there as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2017 11:53:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2017-01-09:blog/mozilla-foss-unconference.html</guid><category>mozilla</category><category>remo</category><category>foss</category></item><item><title>Talk on contributing to Mozilla Marionette</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/talk-contributing-mozilla-marionette.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I've always felt that newbies find it very difficult to get started into any Open Source project. If we talk specifically about code-contribution; which is an essential part of the entire ecosystem, then the no. of people are not enough. I've always found myself surrounded by a bunch of folks who wanted to contribute in Open Source software; and thus asking me questions about how to find bugs, where to get started, etc. One of the most difficult thing they told me is that they don't understand project well enough and thus are not able to recognize on how to get ahead with a particular bug.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am currently contributing to Mozilla Marionette which is an automation driver for Mozilla's Gecko engine. You can read about my experience on that in blog post &lt;a class="reference external" href="/getting-started-marionette.html"&gt;Getting started with Marionette&lt;/a&gt; &amp;amp; &lt;a class="reference external" href="/contributing-marionette-firefox-ui-tests.html"&gt;Contributing more to Marionette and Firefox UI Tests&lt;/a&gt;. I recently decided to give a talk explaining people about Marionette.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I delivered a talk at PyDelhi Meetup (one of the Open Source group I'm actively volunteering for :) ). The talk was scheduled for November 27, 2016. My talk was from 3:30 PM - 4:30 PM IST. In the end there was  a QA session where some people came forward to ask questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some photos of the event:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Sanyam speaking on Mozilla Marionette &amp;amp; Firefox UI Test" class="align-center" src="images/mozilla-marionette-talk_1.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Crowd willing to learn about contributing to Marionette" class="align-center" src="images/mozilla-marionette-talk_2.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Crowd willing to learn about contributing to Marionette" class="align-center" src="images/mozilla-marionette-talk_3.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Crowd willing to learn about contributing to Marionette" class="align-center" src="images/mozilla-marionette-talk_4.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the most important thing I felt is people hesitate in asking questions. This is because after the QA was officialy over, a lot of people came to me with specific questions and told that they were hesistant during QA session. So for those folks, just remember:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
He who asks a question is a fool for five minutes; he who does not ask a question remains a fool forever.
 Chinese Proverb&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than that, we're all friends :) So, come and clear your doubts! Ask me anything. No one is judging you on the basis of questions you ask. It's more important that you try, rather than the fear of failiure stop you from even taking the first step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who missed the talk, I've tried to process the video and uploaded it on Youtube (That's why this update took so much time).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can watch the talk on Youtube (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://youtu.be/l1tZaud0GO4"&gt;https://youtu.be/l1tZaud0GO4&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;
    &lt;iframe width="600" height="400" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/l1tZaud0GO4" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;
    &lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/center&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your comments are much appreciated. Tell me if this session helped you, or how further sessions could be improved!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 05 Dec 2016 01:53:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2016-12-05:blog/talk-contributing-mozilla-marionette.html</guid><category>mozilla</category><category>marionette</category><category>python</category><category>remo</category></item><item><title>Mozilla's Equal Rating Challenge</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/mozilla-equal-rating-challenge.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;The event took place at Hotel Lalit, New Delhi on November 18, 2016. Once again we got a chance to meet Jochai (one of the Mozilla staff) &lt;a class="reference external" href="/mozcoffee-v6-with-sara-jochai.html"&gt;after around 6 months&lt;/a&gt; and he recognized me :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The event was powered by SFLC (Software Freedom Law Centre) &amp;amp; Mozilla. Local community volunteers (Mozpacers) helped with the registration.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Mozilla Equal Rating Challenge" class="align-center" src="images/mozilla-equal-rating-challenge-1.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The event began at 3:00 PM where Jochai introduced people to the problem on making Internet accessible to everyone. After his kick off speech, there was a panel discussion where this issue was discussed. Jochai Ben-Avie, Mishi Choudhary and Smriti Parsheera were speakers. After the panel discussion, people came forward with their questions and got responses from the panel members.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Mozilla Equal Rating Challenge" class="align-center" src="images/mozilla-equal-rating-challenge-2.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that we had tea and a great disccussion with Jochai. We also talked with SFLC team to conduct an event where they can explain about different form to Open Source LISENCE to people and how are they different from each other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We soon plan to have an integrated event with SFLC team where Mozillians would tell about Open Web and community structuring and they will tell about FOSS Laws.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Mozilla Equal Rating Challenge" class="align-center" src="images/mozilla-equal-rating-challenge-3.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was a really good experience all together!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2016 13:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2016-11-26:blog/mozilla-equal-rating-challenge.html</guid><category>mozilla</category><category>mozilla-rep</category><category>remo</category></item><item><title>Mozilla Rep Mentorship Meeting 2</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/mozilla-rep-mentorship-meeting-2.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Today I had another online meeting with my Mozilla Reps Mentor Biraj from 6:00 PM - 6:30 PM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the Minutes of Meeting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;He reviewed initial set of goals I've set.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I told about my current contributions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We discussed about conducting an online and an offline event.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I plan to conduct an event teaching people about Marionette and it's usage so that they can further contribute to gecko engine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can refer to my intial post for the &lt;a class="reference external" href="/mozilla-rep-goals-1.html"&gt;goals I set as a Mozilla Rep&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 12 Nov 2016 06:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2016-11-12:blog/mozilla-rep-mentorship-meeting-2.html</guid><category>mozilla</category><category>mozilla-rep</category><category>remo</category></item><item><title>Mozilla @StoryMirror Youth Creative Conclave</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/mozilla-story-mirror-youth-creative-conclave.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;We had an amazing event scheduled on October 8, 2016 at Hansraj college in Delhi University. I reached the venue at 10:00 AM where I found Anup and other Mozillians preparing for the event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Mozilla Story Mirror youth creative" class="align-center" src="images/mozilla-youth-creative-1.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had three talks scheduled. First one was by Anup; where he introducted people to Mozilla and world of Open Source. We discussed about Open Web and privacy issues; and the role of Mozilla is shaping the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Anup speaking at Mozilla Story Mirror youth creative" class="align-center" src="images/mozilla-youth-creative-2.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Crowd at Mozilla Story Mirror youth creative" class="align-center" src="images/mozilla-youth-creative-3.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next session was taken by me where we discussed about DVCS (Distributed Version Control System) Git which is used in almost every other software product for versioning purposes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Sanyam speaking at Mozilla Story Mirror youth creative" class="align-center" src="images/mozilla-youth-creative-4.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Sanyam telling about his contribution story in Mozilla Story Mirror youth creative" class="align-center" src="images/mozilla-youth-creative-5.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last session was taken by Rajeev where he discussed about local community Mozilla Delhi (Mozpacers) and how people can join in and learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Rajeev speaking at Mozilla Story Mirror youth creative" class="align-center" src="images/mozilla-youth-creative-6.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the event there were a lot of students coming to learn about &amp;quot;How to contribute in Open Source&amp;quot;. Many of them inquired about contributing code to Open Source projects. I guided them the best I could and referred them to resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The event was a great success :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 15 Oct 2016 21:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2016-10-15:blog/mozilla-story-mirror-youth-creative-conclave.html</guid><category>mozilla</category><category>mozilla-rep</category><category>remo</category></item><item><title>Goals as a Mozilla Rep for fourth quarter of 2016!</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/mozilla-rep-goals-1.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I was given this task by my mentor to write down my goals as a Mozilla Rep and then track down my activities every quarter to know where I'm heading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, for the last quarter of 2016, the areas where I'd be focusing on are the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contribute code actively &amp;amp; extensively in one of the modules of Mozilla's gecko engine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Learn about different tracks on Activate Mozilla Campaign and spread awareness among others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Improve upon my public speaking skills; giving back knowledge to the community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Motivate &amp;amp; help others to contribute to Mozilla.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advance deeper into leadership startegies and techniques.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope that in this quarter, I'll be able to work through majority of goals mentioned above.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the end of the quarter, I'll track my progress through the above checklist.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 12 Oct 2016 02:42:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2016-10-12:blog/mozilla-rep-goals-1.html</guid><category>mozilla</category><category>remo</category></item><item><title>Contributing more to Marionette and Firefox UI Tests</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/contributing-marionette-firefox-ui-tests.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;If you don't know about Marionette; you can read my &lt;a class="reference external" href="/getting-started-marionette.html"&gt;previous blog post here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been recently given some follow-up bugs by my mentor. I've just finished up fixing this bug:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1298800"&gt;Add support for callbacks to restart() and quit() methods of Marionette&lt;/a&gt;. Now I've picked up a follow up bug to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1298803"&gt;Add a test to quit firefox&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While trying to fix this bug, I reported two bugs in the Marionette component (&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1309556"&gt;Bug 1309556&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1309141"&gt;Bug 1309141&lt;/a&gt;) which blocks my current bug. So, I'll be first fixing up my reported bugs and then come back to this follow up bug which is assigned to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Till now, the journey in contributing to Marionette has been really awesome and I learned quite a lot of things. I got a chance to read a lot of code and I'm really impressed by the writing styles of the developers. The code base is very neat and definitely good for people who want to see some real test cases in action (something which was not being explained in those &lt;em&gt;Testing 101 talks&lt;/em&gt;) and also improve upon their Python skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to thank Henrik [:whimboo] who is my mentor and guided me so patiently &amp;amp; helped in resolving all my doubts. I'm also reading more about &lt;cite&gt;mach&lt;/cite&gt; command line tool and &lt;cite&gt;marionette&lt;/cite&gt; in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently also came accross &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Firefox Puppeteer&lt;/tt&gt; which is a library built upon the existing &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Marionette Python Client&lt;/tt&gt;. More appropriately; you can write &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Firefox UI tests&lt;/tt&gt; for the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;chrome components&lt;/tt&gt; using &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Puppetteer&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm still to read more about this and I hope at that point of time I'll be able to join all the &lt;em&gt;learning dots&lt;/em&gt; and explain it all in my next blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 06 Oct 2016 00:53:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2016-10-06:blog/contributing-marionette-firefox-ui-tests.html</guid><category>mozilla</category><category>marionette</category><category>python</category></item><item><title>Volunteering for PyCon India 2016</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/pycon-india-2016.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Going back in time; October 3, 2015 in Bangalore; Last day of PyCon India 2015; someone told -- &amp;quot;It takes 9 months to organize PyCon India&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At that time, 9 months looked like a lot of time to me and I thought may be 4-5 months should be good enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming back; 2016 -- PyCon India was organized in Delhi. And boy; behind the scenes these 3 day event took so much time -- so much preperations. I remember working on various stuff with other volunteers in PyDelhi meet-ups; sometimes hangout calls with other volunteers late night. And certainly realized that organizing an event such as PyCon India is not a child's play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This PyCon India helped me in learning organizational skills. Organizing an event such as PyCon India, takes so much effort from people having diversified skill set. From venue to food tasting; I was fortunate enough to see it all. So, let's get into the journey of this 3 day event!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="day-0-pycon-india-workshop-tutorials"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Day 0 -- PyCon India Workshop / Tutorials&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Officially, PyCon India begins! I reached the venue at 7 AM and found Akkshay telling volunteers what to do. We had a look at all the arrangements including DevSprints hall, food, room for Open Spaces and kids Zone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were workshops going on parallelly in 3 different tracks. Also there were bunch of folks learning to contribute in Open Source in PyCon India DevSprints. I was in the DevSprints for most of the time; (sometimes running from one audi to another check the status of the talks and helping with various stuff; as much as I could do).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In afternoon, we started preparing swag kits for PyCon India attendees &amp;amp; it was quite fun.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the evening, we had a Volunteers meet to discuss -- 'What went wrong?', 'How could we correct that for the other two days?', etc. Session Chairs were assigned for each hall and volunteers were explained about their respective work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="day-1-conference-day-1"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Day 1 -- Conference Day 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I reached JNU at 7 AM. I started preparing up to do a live social media feed of all the happening in PyCon India. At around 8 AM, the registrations began. Me and Hans started clicking pictures and posting them on the Social Media. Here is a picture of me trying to do a live social media feed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Sanyam trying to do a live social media feed" class="align-center" src="images/pycon-india-2016-1.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of the day went running across the venue &amp;amp; helping with anything &amp;amp; everything. We also had a discussion on Python Express -- how to reach more audience and spread the love of Open Source and Python. Here is a picture of me while recording the MoM for the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Sanyam making MoM for Python Express discussion" class="align-center" src="images/pycon-india-2016-2.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the evening we went for Volunteers dinner and had a lot of fun!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="day-2-conference-day-2"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Day 2 -- Conference Day 2&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Officially the last day of PyCon India 2016; I could already sense the sadness of friends parting apart for another year. I reached the venue at 7:00 PM and today we missed the first keynote. Amit, Sahil and me went to Akshay's home to pick up the PyCon India t-shirts. Till the time we returned, the keynote was already over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At around 11:30 we had the DGPLUG stair case meet :) We met Sirtaj, Kushal's mentor and learned about Kushal's journey in Open Source world. Here is a photo of same:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="DGPLUG stair case meet" class="align-center" src="images/pycon-india-2016-6.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the afternoon, after lunch we started distributing t-shirts. Here are the awesome Pythonistas waiting to grab PyCon India t-shirt. In less than 2 hours we were able to distribute t-shirts to everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="People waiting eagerly to grab awesome PyCon India 2016 t-shirt" class="align-center" src="images/pycon-india-2016-5.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the evening we had discussion about &amp;quot;What things went wrong and how can we improve further?&amp;quot;. Then different communities were welcomed to pitch to conduct PyCon India 2017 in their city. Since no one came forward, PyDelhi took the initiative to conduct PyCon India next year here in Delhi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end I tried to meet every friend and bid adios to them until next year :) It was quite fun and I learned a lot about organizational skills. Here are some photos which marked the last moment of PyCon India 2016!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="The one with VanL and DGPLUG folks" class="align-center" src="images/pycon-india-2016-3.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Another one with DGPLUG folks" class="align-center" src="images/pycon-india-2016-7.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;img alt="Another one with VanL" class="align-center" src="images/pycon-india-2016-4.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This event would not have been possible without the support of the community. So, I want to thank all the volunteers who came forward &amp;amp; helped in organizing PyCon India and making it so big. See you all next year in Delhi for PyCon India 2017 and let us make it even more big. Here is an awesome picture with everyone!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Another one with VanL" class="align-center" src="images/pycon-india-2016-8.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With this thought, &lt;cite&gt;CuriousLearner&lt;/cite&gt; signs off :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: I realized so many people knew me by my nick -- and I didn't know them :(&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PPS: Thanks to Kushal and Sayan for the pictures.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 03 Oct 2016 12:27:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2016-10-03:blog/pycon-india-2016.html</guid><category>pycon</category><category>pyconindia</category><category>python</category></item><item><title>Mozilla Rep Mentorship Meeting 1</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/mozilla-rep-mentorship-meeting-1.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Just had the very first Mozilla Rep Mentorship e-meet today. It was scheduled to be on 21/09/16 from 9:30 PM IST to 10:00 PM IST. But I reached home early and it was held from 9:00 PM to 9:30 PM IST.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the Minutes of Meeting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Mentor welcomed to Mozilla Reps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Mentor introduced himself and told about his contribution areas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;I introduced myself and told about my current contribution areas&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;A little discussion on Reps Next&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;dl class="first docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Asked a few questions like&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ul class="first last simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why you joined Mozilla Reps?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What is the motivation behind joining Mozilla?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since how much time you're contributing to Mozilla and in which areas?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are your personal goals for being Mozilla Rep?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the community goals for being Mozilla Rep?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;The mentorship would be for 1 year and for first three months we'll be focussing on developing personal skills and little bit on community goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Post that we'll be focussing majorly on community goals (on both local and global level); organising events etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;I was given task to submit personal and community goals in next 20-30 days&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;These would be updated in every quarter; and would be worked upon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope to learn more about Mozilla, it's product and Open Web through this program. Meanwhile I'm also &lt;a class="reference external" href="/getting-started-marionette.html"&gt;contributing to Marionette&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2016 21:30:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2016-09-21:blog/mozilla-rep-mentorship-meeting-1.html</guid><category>mozilla</category><category>mozilla-rep</category><category>remo</category></item><item><title>Becoming a Mozilla Representative</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/mozilla-rep.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Okay, this was kind of surprising. I applied for Mozilla Reps around 4 months ago but my application was put on hold since at that time, since Mozilla was revamping the Mozilla Reps program as Reps Next and there were not enough mentors available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It so happened today, that I got a mail today in the morning titled &amp;quot;Welcome to Reps Program!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was shocked, opened it up and there I got the news that I'm now a Mozilla Rep and was assigned a mentor under whom I'll be working for next 1 year. I've been contributing to Mozilla from more than 1.5 year(s) now. You can get a &lt;a class="reference external" href="/journey-to-being-a-mozillian.html"&gt;glimpse of my journey here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reps Next program majorly focuses on improving personal skills of the candidate. It's completely revamped version of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://reps.mozilla.org/"&gt;Mozilla Reps Program&lt;/a&gt; and you can know &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://blog.mozilla.org/mozillareps/2016/06/16/repsnext-introduction-video/"&gt;more about it here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've a meeting scheduled with my mentor today at 9:30 PM IST and I'll update about the same in another blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2016 14:53:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2016-09-21:blog/mozilla-rep.html</guid><category>mozilla</category><category>mozilla-rep</category><category>remo</category></item><item><title>Getting started with Marionette</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/getting-started-marionette.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I've recently started contributing to Marionette. It is an automation driver for Mozilla's gecko engine. If you're familiar with tools like Selenium; then Marionette is almost along similar lines. It's written in Python and is easy to get started with. So if you're familiar with Python and looking to contribute; then you can read more about it here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Mozilla/QA/Marionette"&gt;https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Mozilla/QA/Marionette&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've always heard from good developers like &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://saurabh-kumar.com"&gt;Saurabh Kumar&lt;/a&gt; that writing tests should be part of your code. Although it increases the development time at that moment but in the long run, it makes your code more reliable and easy to maintain. Also you're more confident making changes to your software product and chances of breaking something and not recognizing until it is pushed to production is decreased exponentially. I always wanted to learn how to write good software and how to write tests for them; hence Marionette was something I wanted to contribute to and learn about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was introduced to the mentor in early 2016; but after 7th Sem exams I was crushed with a lot of things. Never the less, finally I've started contributing to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been mentored by Henrik Skupin [:whimboo]. I hope I'll be able to learn more about writing test cases and some best practices in coding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first bug in Marionette is &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1271330"&gt;https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1271330&lt;/a&gt; which got landed today in Firefox 49, Firefox 50 and Firefox 51. Although this was a starting patch, but it helped me in learning about navigating my way through the Marionette code and about testing in general.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope to solve more bugs and contribute more to Marionette.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 26 Aug 2016 11:53:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2016-08-26:blog/getting-started-marionette.html</guid><category>mozilla</category><category>marionette</category><category>python</category></item><item><title>PyDelhi Meet and Devsprint</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/pydelhi-meet-devsprint.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;So, I hurried to the venue for the meet from Kidzilla event, but I was late as expected :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I reached, Anuvrat was digging deep into module. I agree I couldn't grasp much, since I reached late.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this we had a Dev Sprint for which we moved to the Computer Lab. The Dev Sprint started with an introduction.
We had a bunch of Raspberry Pis with us, so all participants were divided into groups of four to have one RPi each and everyone started implementing Radio Internet. More info about it can be read here: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://contractorwolf.com/raspberry-pi-radio/"&gt;Rpi Plus Internet radio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we first installed the required modules and tried to set-up RPi. We were able to play the stream directly from Internet. Next part we were targetting at was to make a Python Script and use subprocess to stream the Radio from RPi. Also implementing a GUI was part of the plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But unfortunately, we couldn't do it, because of lack of time and given that most of us had no idea about connecting RPi and figuring out the Internet issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None the less, it was a good experience learning something new.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 04 Apr 2016 17:48:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2016-04-04:blog/pydelhi-meet-devsprint.html</guid><category>FOSS</category><category>PyDelhi</category></item><item><title>KidZilla by MozPacers</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/kidzilla-by-mozpacers.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;On April 2, 2016 we had a day full of interactive learning with kids of Bal Sahyog Orphanage, Cannaught Place, Delhi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I reached at Rajiv Chowk metro at 9:45 AM and found Kona, Saurabh, Kanika, Pushpita and Debarun there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we tried to walk up to the venue and was welcomed by Sandeep who takes care of the Computer Science Department there. We had a bunch of kids waiting enthusiastically to learn new things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They were from different age groups and classes (from 10 years old to 16 years old). So, first session was by Pushpita discussing about Mozilla.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Pushpita talking about Introduction to Mozilla" class="align-center" src="images/kidzilla_1.jpeg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second session was by Kanika on basics of Network and introduction to Internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Kanika talking about Networks" class="align-center" src="images/kidzilla_2.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn't had any session scheduled, but I felt the initial session plan was bit overwhelming for those kids so I suggested Pushpita to use simple terms as much as possible as our main aim was to make students learn. Meanwhile, we were distributing swags to students in between every session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We wanted to make it fruitful for the kids, so we tried to explain the things in the best possible way we could. I just re-iterated through the sessions by Pushpita and Kanika to ensure that the they're able to grasp what we were telling them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Sanyam talking about Mozilla and basics of Internet" class="align-center" src="images/kidzilla_3.jpeg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this, we divided students into groups and then each mozpacer was mentoring kids on designing a webpage with HTML. Me, Kanika, Saurabh, Chirag and Sonal were teaching 4 groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Sanyam teaching kids to code" class="align-center" src="images/kidzilla_4.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a picture of enthusiastic students who were being taught by Chirag and Sonal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Chirag and Sonal teaching to code" class="align-center" src="images/kidzilla_5.jpeg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this, we had an ice breaking session where we had a quiz about what we told in earlier sessions. We divided students into two teams and there was lot of enthusiasm in the teams. Meanwhile, I was very impressed when I saw some kids playing with software like Photoshop. Some were playing games and yet another kid was just bugging me to learn about Bash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this, we had a photo session and then left the venue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is our groupfie :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="MozPacers (Mozilla Delhi) group picture" class="align-center" src="images/kidzilla_6.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had to hurry to go to PyDelhi Meet. (Next post will be on this!)&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2016 12:13:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2016-04-03:blog/kidzilla-by-mozpacers.html</guid><category>FOSS</category><category>Mozilla</category><category>mozpacers</category></item><item><title>Finally Mozilla Dev Tools Bug patched</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/mozilla-dev-tool-bug.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Alright, finally it's done. I patched the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1222937"&gt;Mozilla Dev Tools bug&lt;/a&gt;. with help of my mentor Patrick Brosset (pbro). He was the one who helped me with getting started to land my first patch in Mozilla-Central. He is indeed very helpful and I'm greatful to him for being my mentor. We had regular chat on irc and he helped me in explaining various aspects about this bug, how the files are inter-linked and of course, with my silly doubts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, this bug was essentially spreaded over many files, unlike the very first bug I solved. While I wrote the patch in around 2 days for this, it was stuck due the test I had to write. One after another, storm of exams and other things crushed me so hard that I was not able to write the test for it. But then, I decided to do it and started studying the test file, contacted pbro on irc and took help and there I was with this bug patched.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;pbro also gives me detailed code-review about every patch I write and it helps me a lot in improving my coding skills. I've learned about coding-standards and some really good practices in CSS and JS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I'm gonna pick up some more bugs and learn along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2016 00:53:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2016-03-08:blog/mozilla-dev-tool-bug.html</guid></item><item><title>PyDelhi Conference 2016</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/pydelhi-conf-2016.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;And here I am, at PyDelhi Conference, as a volunteer, as an attendee, as a speaker and what not?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I reached the venue at 7:30 AM and people were already there making arrangements. I and Rishabh started with final set-up regarding our workshop, and testing things out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this, I started going to each audi to set up the speakers and projectors. Me and theskumar were looking out for the connectors for Mac at each audi and other setup. Then we got ready for attending keynote by Kiran, but un-fortunately, I couldn't sit for longer due to preperations for my workshop, which was scheduled just after that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Me, Rishabh and Anuvrat presented workshop on Python for beginners and Mobile as a micro-bit. First, Anuvrat took a quick session on teaching Python for beginners while me and Risabh took the microbit part.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We demonstrated 'kivy-shell' which is developed by Kivy Developers and Qua-non (Akkshay), one of the core-contributors of kivy project helped us with all the initial preperations for this. While the initial set-up took time for everyone, but everyone seemed happy after the workshop. They had a lot of doubts and we tried to answer them in the best possible way we could, in the QA session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, I got to another audi to help. Most of my time in the conference was spent roaming in-between the three audis to help people as a volunteer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had some interesting discussions too with many people, got to learn various things, and overall this was a huge success for the PyDelhi community. Here are some of the pictures from the conference:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the conference all volunteers celebrated with dinner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next we plan to hold PyCon India 2016 here in Delhi, so preperations are in full swing for it, and I'll include that in a later blog post.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2016 00:53:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2016-03-07:blog/pydelhi-conf-2016.html</guid></item><item><title>Moz-Coffee v6 with Sara and Jochai</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/mozcoffee-v6-with-sara-jochai.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Well, this blog post would depict a very wonderful experience! This time, it's not just about MozCoffee v6, it would also depict the preparation phase for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="preparation-phase"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Preparation Phase&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, one fine day, Anup (our community Lead) announces that we would have Mozilla Staff here in Delhi and we've to organize an event in a week. After sometime, Ajay announced that Sara Haghdoosti and  Jochai Ben-Avie would be here and we've just 5 days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we had regular calls about everything, from logistics to how the event would be executed. We had to decide a venue, send invites to people, get their confirmation, plan for waiting list etc. And we had just 5 days. We delegated the work and each core-contributor of the community had shown such an enthusiasm to accomplish each and every task alloted to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We decided to make a presentation about our community so that we can release it on event day for everyone along with our website. We decided to have it on reveal JS.
Pushpita and Yash were responsible for making content. Sonal, Kanika and Saurabh were responsible for putting them in the reveal slides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would like to mention that none of those mozpacers knew how revealJS works, but I'm happy that they came forward to not only learn it, but implement and execute the task so smoothly. I provided them with the initial set-up of reveal and took an online session where I explained them how reveal JS works &amp;amp; provided them some resources. I was really very happy that they took extra time from regular activities like college to learn reveal and make the slides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile we decided to release our community website in beta on this day. I remember, how me and Nikhil were pushing commits daily, co-ordinating with core-contributors to finish up their tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, Ajay and Bhuvnesh, were looking for a venue, Saurabh made a form for the people and I shooted the mails to people for invites, confirmation and then later RSVP.
Kanika made a poster for spreading the word about the event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite this event being on Tuesday and given that we started to plan the event just 5 days before, we received an enormous response. We're so happy to see so many upcoming people interested in Open Source.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="the-event-day"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Event Day&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had a long waiting list for the event, and finally was the event day. Me and Pushpita reached the venue early and started making arrangements. After sometime, Bhuvnesh, Nikhil, Kanika, Saurabh and Manraj were there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We again delegated the responses and set-up a registration desk to guide people who were confirmed for the event.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then, around 3:00 PM, Ajay arrived with Sara and Jochai from Mozilla and they were too excited to meet everyone. After a light refreshment, they moved on to the presentation area.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Sara and Jochai" class="align-center" src="images/moz-coffee-v6_2.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ajay started with introduction to Mozilla and it's mission. What is Open Web, need for it, how Mozilla is helping in it. Then he told about the community, various communication channels, how people can contribute to Open Source and contribution pathways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, we had WoMoz session where Pushpita explained about participation of women in Mozilla, importance of women empowerment and encouraged more women to come forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this, our technical team came up on the stage. I explained everyone about the projects we're working on. Manraj told about the Community Manager app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="MozPacers Tech Contributors" class="align-center" src="images/moz-coffee-v6_1.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We released the beta version of our site, invited people to contribute by finding and patching bugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="MozPacers Tech Contributors" class="align-center" src="images/moz-coffee-v6_4.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that Sara and Jochai educated attendees about Internet Privacy , advocacy and also how India is playing major and significant role on Web Advocacy and Openness. We had a small exercise as told by Sara where everyone got up and we learnt about Web Advocacy and Internet Privacy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Sara and Jochai" class="align-center" src="images/moz-coffee-v6_3.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this, we had two separate help desks set-up for Technical and Non-Technical respectively. And here we released another project developed in just those 5 days: Moz-Connect (This would be expanded more). We collected details of everyone through &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/mozpacers/moz-connect"&gt;Moz-Connect&lt;/a&gt;, later we'll have an automated system set up to invite contributors (if they willingly selected to volunteer for Mozilla in the Moz-Connect) via mail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Me, Nikhil and Manraj were there on Tech Desk and Kanika, Pushpita were there on the non-tech desks. Met a lot of people who inquired about how to contribute, some people specifically were interested in the tech we're using and asking why we chose them. We tried to answer their queries in the best possible way we could.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Haven't really told anyone till now that how much successful we were in this phase of Moz-Connect. So, I'll tell in this blog post! Once I reached back home and merged the database, then I saw the content filled in MozConnect, many people filled in the queries section that &amp;quot;there queries were already resolved on the help desks&amp;quot; and that made me really happy. (Excellent work there team! ;))&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had a photo session with everyone :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="MozCofee v6 attendees" class="align-center" src="images/moz-coffee-v6_6.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At around 5PM we had refreshments for everyone. Meanwhile, Sara, Jochai, Ajay and Bhuvnesh were discussing about the community and how we can help even outside the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In last few hours, all core-contributors had a talk with Sara and Jochai about problems we're facing, how we started, what are the motivations, what is the future road-map etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Ajay, Sara and Jochai" class="align-center" src="images/moz-coffee-v6_5.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we had another round of photo session and then left the venue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2016 20:15:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2016-02-16:blog/mozcoffee-v6-with-sara-jochai.html</guid><category>fsa</category><category>Mozilla</category><category>mozpacers</category></item><item><title>Patched first bug for mozilla-central</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/patched-first-bug-for-mozilla-central.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Well, everything seems difficult until you start!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How will I make a patch? Will I ever able to understand that code? Will
I really able to do it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone has these questions in mind and various others, while
struggling to contribute to a huge code-base like that of Mozilla. So,
recently I started reading stuff from MDN (Mozilla Developer Network)
and then with bugsahoy and bugzilla, started figuring out
good-first-bugs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difficulty was, it uses such terms, I haven't even heard of! So, I
was actually really afraid of commenting that I want to pick it up. But
now, I was really frustrated with myself, and thought to give it a try
to any bug, people would definitely help me, and I will figure a way
out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I reached &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://bugzilla.mozilla.org/show_bug.cgi?id=1221494"&gt;this
bug&lt;/a&gt; where
enough of the instructions were already there, and it seemed like a very
quick fix. This was a CSS bug in animation inspector of developer tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having submitted a patch, I got review for my code and accordingly I did
the changes, and on Feb 1, 2016. This patch got accepted :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I'm working on another bug which is on JS in the animation inspector
| Dev tools. It's almost done, and I hope I would submit one more patch
soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 05 Feb 2016 13:41:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2016-02-05:blog/patched-first-bug-for-mozilla-central.html</guid></item><item><title>MozPacers at MSIT</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/mozpacers-at-msit.html</link><description>&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Our MozPacers (Mozilla Delhi) community conducted an event today at MSIT (Mahraja Surajmal Institute of Technology).&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;We planned various events for students and the itinerary is as follows:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Intro to Mozilla, it's mission and Open Web - Delivered by Bhuvnesh and Manraj&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Promoting Womoz and gathering more women contributors - By Ashu and Sonal&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Learning version control with Git - By me; Sanyam&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Webmaker tools - By Saurabh&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I reached the venue at 11:30 AM. We made some arrangements and till
the students gathered, it was already around 12:50 PM. Initial session
was started by Bhuvnesh about intro to Mozilla, it's mission, privacy
etc. Then Manraj shared about his experience in contributing to Mozilla
and a little bit about his visit to Leadership summit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In between we had quiz session on Mozilla, where we distributed swags
for whoever comes up with the correct answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then Sonal and Ashu encouraged more women contributors to come forward
and enlightened others about their contribution in the community. They
told about various pathways to contribute; it's not about just patching
bugs, they told how they are doing documentation in the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next session was taken by me about Intro to version control system,
specifically Git. I told about basics of Git, some things about
Mercurial (since that is what Mozilla is using).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then Saurabh took session on Webmaker tools like Thimble, X-ray goggles
etc. and encouraged students to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we had a sort of open house session where we took in questions from
people, and answered them. Bhuvnesh, Nikhil, Manraj, Saurabh and me
answered their queries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I told about my exprience with Mozilla, how I'm about the land
my first patch for Mozilla central, what all I learned, what's in it to
contribute to FOSS etc. I shared about how I fiddled to contribute, why
it is essential to ask questions etc. I told them about IRC and Mailing
list guidelines, covering basics of Bugzilla. I hope this would help
them :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many students seemed to be enthusiastic enough to join MozPacers and
learn from the community, and I hope we will soon see more faces in the
next MozCofee meetup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, yeah, need to now have a closer look at mails, I'm expecting MSIT
people would ping us now for help :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll update this post with pictures from the event soon :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 30 Jan 2016 21:48:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2016-01-30:blog/mozpacers-at-msit.html</guid></item><item><title>PyDelhi Birthday Bash!</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/pydelhi-birthday-bash.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;And here it is! We just completed 1 year of regular meetups at PyDelhi.
We organized various workshops, meet-ups, events etc. in the past one
year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had the meet on 9th Jan, 2016. The venue was Fueled. We gathered
there and started the introduction outside the office. After the
introduction session, we got inside and we had a small presentation
about PyDelhi delivered by Rishabh, Ashutosh and me, where we explained
about PyDelhi, PyCon India, volunteering, how to contribute, various
events by PyDelhi in 2015 etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we had a session where we explained how we used Python in 2015 in
our projects. And there were many participants. Some projects were
really good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this, we had the snacks and cake ready! After the party, most of
the people formed groups and were discussing. There were a large group
of students from Amity who just started programming and were looking for
inspiration. Some people just came to me and asked for help. I guided
them in the best possible way I could as per my exprience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon after this, Satyaakam sir told that they would give inspiration and
showed github account of student of PyChill who was in 8th standard. The
repo was full of algos written in Python. He also showed the website
that student made for PyChill. Again, I realized what Mr. Anuvrat told
me, &amp;quot;Hum to Jhak maar rahe hai!&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was really inspiring for me as well and provided enough motivation
to start working hard. After this, we had volunteers sitting around and
completing various tasks for the PyDelhi Conference. We set up explara
account, made up logo, pamphlets, resolved various issues on the repo,
made list of people for reviewing the CFPs etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had a discussion on what all needs to be done with theskumar and then
left.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 13 Jan 2016 00:52:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2016-01-13:blog/pydelhi-birthday-bash.html</guid></item><item><title>Learning from Anup's MozFest Experience</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/learning-from-anups-mozfest-experience.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;(Image Courtesy: wiki.mozilla.org)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My journey in Mozilla has been quite awesome and interesting till now.
I've come to learn a lot of things, met like-minded people, shared ideas
with them, gave talks which helped a lot in improving upon my skills as
an organizer, leader, speaker, programmer and what not! and I hope it
was beneficial to the community as well. This week I also got my name in
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.mozilla.org/credits/"&gt;Mozilla about:credits&lt;/a&gt;, and that's
just because of continuous support from the local community and guidance
of Anup, Ajay and Bhuvnesh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anup, our community mentor, got a chance to attend MozFest 2015. Last
Saturday, he took an online session on vidyo, where he enlightened us
about his learning in MozFest. He told us about various session he
attended and his participation in the program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is about my thoughts and learning through Anup's online
session about Leaders, Leadership and participation in the community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I've been a Tech SIG Lead in my local community (MozPacers), but
I think Leaders are not different from other community members. I
believe everyone is a leader, and it is the participation of the
community members which acts as a pillar to the community. Not a single
person could be a leader and not a single person depicts leadership
qualities that take a community too far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In every community, I believe only participation by different members
helps in progressing and accomplishing any task. Anup is very right when
he says &amp;quot;Participation is the core of any program&amp;quot;. Everyone is a leader
in the community and everyone makes decision which certainly affects
every other member of the community. It is the power of these decisions
collaboratively, which every community member make, that develop the
whole community and lead it to the right direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mentors are always there to guide the community members; but the
distributed leadership where every member puts up his/her ideas reflects
what truly leadership is. It is just about coming-forward and presenting
one's views. When this distributed leadership through participation is
collaborated, and everyone devotes something, learn from others; the
whole group benefits and move forward together. This is what reflects
the true meaning of participation and leadership.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my local community too, I've learned quite a lot from my fellow
Mozillians. We've collaborated on various stuff, whether it is
Peer-to-Peer learning session, developing on projects for the community
or just lending a helping hand in almost any task. It is this binding
power (Participation) of team members which I've witnessed, has helped
in growing up the community where people learn and are equally motivated
to lead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, just to summarize my learning from Anup's session:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Leadership is not a single trait that a single person possess, it is
the collaborative effort of the whole group, where they participate,
learn and grow together.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I joined MozPacers when it was really in it's initial phase. Met Ajay,
Anup and Bhuvnesh who told me that a website is to be needed for
MozPacers, and that's how we made the initial wireframe in the first
meet itself and my contributions started. If you want to know about my
journey, then please read: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://erSanyamKhurana.wordpress.com/2015/07/14/journey-to-being-a-mozillian/"&gt;My Journey to being a
Mozillian&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="what-makes-me-an-effective-contributor"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What makes me an effective contributor?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Helped in revamping MozPacers, Mozilla Delhi Community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Got &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://mozillians.org/en-US/u/CuriousLearner/"&gt;vouched&lt;/a&gt; and
also got my name listed in &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.mozilla.org/credits/"&gt;Mozilla
about:credits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Spoke at Mozilla Dev Sprints on Git, git-flow etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Got to Jaipur Stumbling Trip to contribute to Mozilla Stumbler&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Won Mozilla Stumbler v1.0 Delhi NCR with more than 50,000 reports
submitted till that time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Still contributing to Stumbler. Also reported issues on official
repo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Selected as Contributor of the Month (July 2015)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Presently Technical SIG Lead of mozpacers&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Represented MozPacers at AngelHack where we developed FirefoxOS app
NGO Man to help NGOs in efficiently managing their resources.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contributed to MozPacers website (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mozpacers.org"&gt;http://www.mozpacers.org&lt;/a&gt;) ,
slackbot and mass e-mail sender &amp;amp; other few projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enlightened people about Contribution pathways and brought my friends
in the community to contribute in Mozilla's mission.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As SIG Lead, I mentor new comers in the community and learn myself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Got many of my friends including Nikhil, Vikram, Manraj, Akansh and
others in getting started with contributions and being involved with
MozPacers, and now they are now core-contributors of the community.
Nikhil is now Tech SIG Lead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Believes is FOSS's &amp;quot;Giving back to the community&amp;quot;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Managing github organization of MozPacers; reviewing code and
guidelines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Created online infrastructure and set-up for MozPacers community.
Setting up domain, official e-mails, website, bots etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Managing various communication channels of MozPacers viz Slack,
trello etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Received another vouch from Ajay.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="how-mozpacers-is-an-effective-community"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How MozPacers is an effective community?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Contributed more than 19 lac (19,00,000) reports in Mozilla Stumbler.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have shown up as the Most Active community in Northern India&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Have volunteers from Punjab, Himachal Pradesh, Delhi, Haryana,
Faridabad and other cities/states in Northern India.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Proven Track record of events like Mozilla MozCoffee taking place at
least once every month. Along with other events like Dev Sprints,
hackathons etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People are given chance to speak about their contributions and teach
other people.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Diversity both in terms of geography and gender.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Strengthening the WoMoz.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On-going projects like Community Manager to help the other
communities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lending a helping hand and collaborating with other communities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A proper process to help newbies in getting-involved and providing 1
on 1 mentoring sessions to them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More people joining in every month.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MozCofee have more than 30+ people and in some events we get 50-60+
people as well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We have strength of 30+ Core-Contributors of the community.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://wiki.mozilla.org/Mozilla_Delhi"&gt;proper organization
structure&lt;/a&gt; involved to
help in better tracking of contributors and giving them shoulder tap
when needed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now Anup would also take another session on his learning in specific
programs he attended at MozFest. He would tell about the IceBerg Model
and other things which I'm really looking forward to learn about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 25 Nov 2015 11:20:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2015-11-25:blog/learning-from-anups-mozfest-experience.html</guid><category>FOSS</category><category>mozfest</category><category>Mozilla</category><category>mozpacers</category></item><item><title>FSA Community Engagement Meet-up</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/fsa-community-engagement-meet-up.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Ah, well, coudn't write about this, as I had my exams and project
submissions. But yeah, here it is. #FSADreamTeam. This would be a quick
post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On November 14 and 15, we had people for FSA Community Engagement here
in Delhi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We had Santosh, Kritika and Tanay here in Delhi. Well, I had my exams
and wasn't sure, if I should go, but then I went for both days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="day-0"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;DAY 0&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I reached the venue well before time and inquired Santosh about where
we're meeting. I got to the place. We started our discussion about FSA
program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We discussed about what all is expected through FSA Program and how we
can improve it. Also we started doing SWOT (Strength, Weakness,
Opportunity, Threats) Analysis of FSA Program. Un-fortunately, due to
exams, not enough people joined on Saturday. But as soon as we started
tweeting, people from MozPacers community started collaborating online
despite of exams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After discussing on Strength and Weakness Analysis, we had our Lunch,
and then we left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="day-1"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;DAY 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On this day, we had many members joined in for discussion. Ajay, Anup,
Bhuvnesh, Tanshul, Kunal, Pushpita also joined. From the previous day,
we carried on SWOT Analysis. We had a discussion on FSA Program,
opportunities which are expected and also how we can improve on it. Also
we had discussion on collaborating with other communities and strengthen
the Mozilla's mission.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="FSA community engagement" src="images/fsa-community-meetup-1.jpeg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After lunch, we presented our idea of Community Manager App, which
MozPacers are planning to make in order to efficiently manage all the
community statistics. We would first have a pilot run in our local
community and then make it configurable for every community. That would
help in efficiently managing contributions and recognizing contributions
in every local community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="FSA community engagement" src="images/fsa-community-meetup-2.jpeg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone then said good-bye and we left the venue. I was happy to meet
new people and learn from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All our discussions are mentioned here:
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://public.etherpad-mozilla.org/p/delhi"&gt;https://public.etherpad-mozilla.org/p/delhi&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 24 Nov 2015 20:15:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2015-11-24:blog/fsa-community-engagement-meet-up.html</guid><category>fsa</category><category>Mozilla</category><category>mozpacers</category></item><item><title>Mozilla Dev Sprint v3.0</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/mozilla-dev-sprint-v3-0.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Writing after a long time. Have been occupied by a lot of things and
that's why the official site of Mozilla Delhi, mozpacers.org, (Yes, we
got that domain a while ago) was never being ready for release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The event section integration and stuff was causing a lot of problem.
Nikhil was facing a lot of issues on front-end and there was not good
communication online so that we both can together collaborate physically
and complete it. That's why, we requested for a mini Dev Sprint, and
here it was.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Nikhil, me and Bhuvnesh" class="align-center" src="images/mozilla-dev-sprint-v3.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mozilla Dev Sprint v3.0 held at Cvent, Gurgaon on 18th Oct 2015. We both
reached at 10:30 AM sharp, and met Bhuvnesh. We then got to the
conference room which was where we were supposed to code.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we started. As expected, touching our own code after few months left
us buzzard, and one hour was spent figuring out what needed to be done
exactly. After that, Nikhil started to adjust for the overall styling
for Events section and I was modifying the API as requested by Nikhil to
accommodate for the details of a single event to be displayed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Till 12:30 PM, I was able to figure out the changes to be made in the
API. Then we both were decided about how exactly the page should look
like for a single event. We came up with this wireframe and started
working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Wireframe for displaying single events on Mozpacers.org" class="align-center" src="images/mozilla-dev-sprint-v3_1.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We decided to fill our database with actual values. So, Bhuvnesh started
collecting all the details and making JSON for it. I was reviewing the
PR's already made on the repo and Nikhil was working on the front-end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soon, I realized Nikhil's fork was around 50 commits behind the main
repo and now we were ready for merge conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around 6:30 PM everything was functional and we were resolving merge
conflicts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We decided to make this functional site an alpha v0.1 release. Though
most of the things are breaking, but at least the site is functional. :)
We left Cvent at 7:30 PM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next day, we had a meeting with core-contributors about general
instructions on PR and commits on github repo and if everyone comes
forward we hope to complete the beta release by next Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2015 16:38:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2015-10-21:blog/mozilla-dev-sprint-v3-0.html</guid><category>FOSS</category><category>Mozilla</category><category>Open Source</category></item><item><title>Mozilla Stumbling in Jaipur</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/mozilla-stumbling-in-jaipur.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I got to Jaipur Stumbling trip which was majorly sponsored by Mozilla.
Here is a full detail about our journey. Our main motive was to collect
at least 10k reports for the upcoming Mozilla Stumbler Project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="day-0"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;DAY 0&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Starting of my journey became complex as some last minute changes caused
trouble for me to reach Kashmere Gate, from where we had to leave
together for Jaipur. After some jiggling I was able to book Uber and
left my house at 3:50 AM. Reached Kashmere Gate at 4:18 AM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Found the Traveller, met people and we left around 4:35 from there. On
the way picked up Vikram and then headed towards Gurgaon where Bhuvnesh
and others were waiting. Well, and then suddenly our tire got punctured.
Well normal people get dis-heartened, but MozPacers just utilized that
time clicking selfies. One of them is here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Jaipur stumbling" class="align-center" src="images/mozilla-stumbling-jaipur_1.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the tire was changed, we moved on and reached Gurgaon at 6:30 AM,
picked up Bhuvnesh and others and moved on our journey. We played some
music on the go, decided on some movie to watch, but then every other
person could be seen sleeping and no one was watching movie.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After waking up, we continued to play cards and a Game where everyone
had to speak only in Hindi, no English words. We stopped at around 9:00
AM in a nearby Dhaba, and grabbed some tea/coffe and snacks. We moved on
and reached hotel Mansingh at 12:30 PM. Got one hour to freshen up.
Then, we decided not to have lunch and go directly to visit forts since
visitors were allowed only till 5 PM and we didn't have enough time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We got to Jantar Mantar and got to see many instruments that helped
tracking even the celestial objects. Also got to know that Jaipur was
the first city that was built with a proper plan. We also got to
Nahargarh Fort and enjoyed the awesome view. We also wen to Amer Fort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At around 6:00 PM all of us were hungry, and stopped by a nearby shop
for some snacks. We also got to look Jal Mahal and Hawa Mahal from
outside. We got back to hotel and people got to their rooms to rest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tanshul and I decided to go for swimming. So, we got ready and went for
swimming. Well, I forgot some strokes, seemed like I had some fear of
water returned, but soon enough I was able to overcome that. Tried
different strokes like freestyle, froggy etc. and practiced some basic
stuff. Then we returned to our rooms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just got to bed, and then suddenly someone entered the room. It was
Nikhil, telling that we have a meeting at the conference room and I've
to hurry. I got to the place, and we had some discussion on the website
project and also about involving new contributors. Since we had many new
people with us, we told them what was going on in the community and
status of various things we are planning. We then had dinner and decided
to carry on the discussion about the website project in the room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At 11:30 PM, we gathered in a common room, on a single bed and had that
discussion. After that, Anoop &amp;amp; Ajay started telling stories of Ghost.
Not to forget that this left some people in so much fear that they slept
with keeping lights of their room on. :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="day-1"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;DAY 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around 12:30 AM I got bored and left to sleep since it was more than
full day I got to sleep. Later, Vikram came and then around 1 AM I got
to sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Around 4:30 AM I got up, and took a bath. At around 5:30 AM I was ready,
got off the room and roamed in the lobby area for some time. No one was
there :( At around 7:00 AM I got inside room, Vikram was sleeping so I
though to roam outside only, I got outside but this time forgot to take
the keys :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I returned at around 7:30 AM and then rang the bell, Vikram got up to
open the door and then got ready. We got out for breakfast and then
decided to meet at 10:00 AM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We then shooted community videos on Stumbling experience. Clicked some
pictures in and around hotel and then left to visit City Palace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, we got a guide (We called him MozGuide) there who helped us
explored the place and we got to see various places where different
movies like Jodha Akbar was shot.Here is a picture of MozPacers with
MozGuide.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;img alt="Jaipur stumbling" class="align-center" src="images/mozilla-stumbling-jaipur_2.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We left Jaipur at around 2:30 PM. The journey continued and suddenly
something happened.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was on the last seat as usual and looked back and realized that Diesel
was leaking. We immediately stopped and got that the grip of tyre weared
off. Now this caused us a major problem. We went back and forth to
various shops on highway in search of a tyre, and then ultimately at
around 6:30 PM we got to some good shop. After that we got to the
traveller and continued to Delhi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We reached Gurgaon at around 11:30 PM. Meanwhile we were playing
different games like Truth &amp;amp; Dare. Me and Vikram got off near AIIMS and
then returned to our homes. I reached around 1:00 AM&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In between the journey we named everything pre-pending it with Moz like
MozWater, MozChor, MozGuide, MozJail, MozFort et all. :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, well, did I forget to mention that I just got declared as the winner
of Mozilla Stumbler v1.0 Delhi NCR? :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a picture while we were in Jaipur:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Jaipur stumbling" class="align-center" src="images/mozilla-stumbling-jaipur_3.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 27 Jul 2015 00:21:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2015-07-27:blog/mozilla-stumbling-in-jaipur.html</guid><category>FOSS</category><category>Mozilla</category><category>Stumbler</category></item><item><title>Journey To Being a Mozillian</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/journey-to-being-a-mozillian.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Few months back, despite of all odds, I attended an event by Mozilla
which was WebMaker event, where I along with my friend Vikram (I
literally had to force him to attend, since the event was far away and
we were tired on that day),  visited to know more about WebMaker Project
and in a hope to start contributing by asking people around. There I met
Anup Kumar Mishra and Ajay Kumar, (both being Mozilla Reps) where they
were telling about WebMaker project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the time, I was struggling to get started to contribute to Mozilla
and they told me to drop a mail, and they would help me. I did that
immediately, and also got help from them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I came to know that they're trying to re-build Mozilla Delhi community
and want some active contributors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was interested and keep attending their MozCofee meet one after the
another. Though didn't get enough time to document each event earlier
due to my exams and then my prior commitments. By the way here is our
recent picture :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="MozPacers (Mozilla Delhi) group picture" class="align-center" src="images/mozilla_delhi_group.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I'll try to summarize all that in this post itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mozilla Delhi started to categorize contributors in two categories, so
as to ease the maintenance of work, as in:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Technical Contributors, who are interested in patching bugs and in
general contributing some Open Source Code&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Non-Technical Contributors, who promote Mozilla and it's various
products. They'll manage all the events, arrangements and other
managerial tasks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though these are not hard-followed in the sense, everyone is free to
work in both categories, no bounds are there and that is awesome,
isn't it? (Keep reading, if you want to join as contributor.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, in order to establish and let people know about Mozilla Delhi,
we decided to build a website representing Mozilla Delhi. For that,
we gathered some more contributors as we needed front-end people,
back-end people, UI/UX designers etc. I reached my developers friends
and told about awesome opportunity to contribute. Thus I invited
Nikhil Handa (as he's good in UI/UX), Manraj Singh (back-end and some
front-end), Akansh Gulati (front-end) and some other people.
Meanwhile, I was also being actively being pinged on facebook by
people to know more about Mozilla Delhi and start contributions. I
was trying my best to guide them further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, we were planning things on slack (mozpacers.slack.com) and
decided to have Dev Sprint v1.0 to decide upon the Website, finalize
the wire-frame, distribute responsibilities, choosing tech stack for
the creation of website, et all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dev Sprint v1.0 was planned to be at Zopper (the same company I'm
doing internship at). Thanks to Co-Founder Surjendu Kuila for
sponsoring Mozilla Delhi's DevSprint v1.0.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we gathered at Zopper and started discussion on the initial
wire-frame and using whiteboard, we tried to gathered more
requirements and listen to what everyone has to say. Different points
were put forward by the community members regarding design,
functionality and other non-functional requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When majority of people agreed upon the design and details, we made a
separate list of those tasks. Those who had some concerns about the
design and functionality were explained the approach. After
brainstorming and lot of discussions we mutually agreed upon a
design.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We decided to go with SPA (Single Page Application) as per the
initial wire-frame, and decided upon technologies to be used for the
creation of the website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All people were not comfortable with any one technology (as
expected), but then everyone was happy to get an opportunity to learn
and implement things. With this motive, we finalized the following
tech stack:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Front-End: HTML, CSS, JS, JQuery, BootStrap + (some other front-end framework, if needed.)&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Back-End: REST API using Flask (micro web framework for Python), MongoDB for the database.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;We also finalized using git to be our version control system in this project and made repo on github.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Earlier, we were using a separate account on github, but then I recently got around the concept of Github Organizations, and I suggested that on our slack channel. People liked it, and we shifted from that account to an Organizational account, where we added contributors. You can visit us on Github (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.Github.com/MozPacers"&gt;www.Github.com/MozPacers&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also decided to use git-flow as it would help us in near future
for better maintenance and everyone was suggested to make features
and work on them. Community members mutually agreed on the official
coding guidelines and structuring of code as per the language they're
coding in. (For example, for Python PEP8 standards).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People started picking out different front-end sections and
implementing them. Most of the front-end is now finished.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile I picked up the back-end and implemented it. Though there
is much more to be done as in integrations with the front-end and
security constraints, I think we've learnt a lot along the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully in DevSprint v2.0 we'll finish the website project and make
it live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you in Delhi and want to contribute? Then join us at Dev Sprint
v2.0. For more details, please follow the official &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.twitter.com/mozpacers"&gt;Mozilla Delhi
channel on twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2015 15:27:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2015-07-14:blog/journey-to-being-a-mozillian.html</guid><category>FOSS</category><category>Mozilla</category></item></channel></rss>