<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Sanyam Khurana</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/</link><description>Curious Learner | FOSS Contributor | Passionate Geek</description><atom:link href="feeds/feeds/personal.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Apr 2015 21:21:00 +0530</lastBuildDate><item><title>Just my inputs on how JMI Internship fair could be better!</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/just-my-inputs-on-how-jmi-internship-fair-could-be-better.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Hey guys,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;First of all, thank you for providing everyone &amp;quot;opportunity&amp;quot; for internships.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Next, I realize, that all the volunteers were really hard working. But unfortunately, all the hard-work was actually not upto the mark just because they were actually doing redundant things and increasing their work.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some of the points I will mention here which would help you in
conducting and managing events better in future that would be helpful
for all of us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, your updates on the event page were in small updates, the
information were updated bit by bit, which was actually troublesome
since last minute updates are too bad to arrange for stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, you allotted slots to people, while it was good approach, you made
that in chronological order which means, which has a lower registration
number (registered earlier) was allotted 3rd slot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, when you collected all the details through Google Forms and had
all that data in CSV then why you chose to make a physical form and made
everyone fill that, that means registering again. ( I mean going for
manual work) when you had everything in a system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, going where the interview were held, there were really hardworking
volunteers, but I'm surprised there was actually no one to tell which
volunteer was actually managing what start-up interview. So people need
to search for the person, which created a mess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, once one volunteer has that form, I and certainly all were
actually blocked, since they cannot actually go to other interview, and
wait till his first interview is over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This actually made the task rather really cumbersome and difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, start-ups closed the vacancies, just taking the
candidates which comes first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, it was really bad, you cannot assume that those who comes first to
you are the best ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyways other candidates have to now change their options which was not
good and then you were changing that in your CSVs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering all these points, I hope you can actually improve upon it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;My input:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Once you had the data in CSV, then you should've just schedule interviews based on the reference number for particular start-up. All are doing B.Tech and a small python script may be was enough to that, isn't it?&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, interviews could clash but then some adjustment could be done
by volunteers and it could be corrected after waiting for some time till
when the current interview gets over ;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, start-ups should not be in a hurry, obviously they need the best
ones, and they shouldn't close their vacancies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you keep on doing the good work and improve in future. Kudos to
your efforts :D It was really great that JMI organized this ;) but a
little more management and devotion of time by start-ups would have made
this an indeed awesome thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: I posted it on my blog as the option for posting it on the event
page was removed.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 25 Apr 2015 21:21:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2015-04-25:blog/just-my-inputs-on-how-jmi-internship-fair-could-be-better.html</guid></item><item><title>Back to Work after 5th sem End Term Exams!</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/back-to-work-after-5th-sem-end-term-exams.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;So, my 5th term end semester exams didn't went well enough! I was just
frustrated about the subjects I was made to study. Even the computer
related subjects are taught with an aim to make students just pass the
exams. Cram it, give exam, pass it and you know it; without any
practical implication, just cram them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, went really awful, I was full of frustration, trying to
figure out what I'm into currently and what I really want to do. Well,
choosing Engineering was my own decision. I chose it so as to learn
something. Probably I'm learning, but I didn't want to learn this way.
The problem is the focus of universities towards making students cram
even the programming languages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I don't really understand their agenda. While I know the concepts
are needed to be strong for any practical implication. But just focusing
on a methodology where  they just make students 'cram' the concepts
rather than understanding and then without any practical implication is
like telling a policemen different ways to catch a thief but never
giving him chance to do so, or better yet, not telling him who to catch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever the heck they're trying to do, now I'm not concerned with it.
I've decided to squeeze out the most of the information they're giving
me and then carry on to learn more and trying to apply the concepts for
a better understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Studying Java this semester was a tough task, my concepts were not clear
till the very last, until I picked up my laptop and decided to write the
code, even if it means I fail in theory exam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And once I wrote it, tried things, then I started understanding it.
Still a lot more to be practically implied, but I'm glad I tried it
against the universities norms of just cramming things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I was highly frustrated, I just needed some inspiration and this
video really helped me to recover and gain a stable mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="margin-top:10px;"&gt;
  &lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.facebook.com/video.php?v=646658398797216&amp;set=vb.426895610773497&amp;type=2&amp;theater" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Okay, so now as I've decided previously, I'll be conducting a HackerRank
contest for all GGSIPU students, which is almost done and details are
being finalized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next, I've decided to keep learning JS and Python and improve upon them.
I really like to code in Python, I've not a solid idea why, but I simply
like it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now, it's time to complete and publish posts on my blog
TheGeekyWay.com which are saved as draft from the past 3 months. Also,
need to carry on some other work I've committed to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, I've some time and I'll utilize it fully to learn and improve.
Inspiration tank is re-fueled :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jan 2015 14:52:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2015-01-08:blog/back-to-work-after-5th-sem-end-term-exams.html</guid></item><item><title>Be Inspired! Keep working hard; Never give up!</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/be-inspired-keep-working-hard-never-give-up.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Well, I just turned on Facebook for a few minutes and interestingly
found a link &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="//www.quora.com/Is-it-too-late-to-start-programming-at-17-if-you-want-to-be-a-top-programmer"&gt;Is it too late to start programming at 17 if you want to
be a top
programmer?&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;
pointing to a post on Quora! I read it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, that's something really awesome!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Believe me, it's very essential in life to keep working towards your
goals, you should always keep on moving. We should always do things
which motivate us! Do, what we actually love to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Work Hard" class="align-center" src="images/work-hard.jpg" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first answer to this question is by Don Pinkus. He was an Engineer
at Facebook and now working on his own project. You can read his &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://medium.com/&amp;#64;donpinkus/when-are-you-too-old-to-become-an-engineer-31db0fdca554"&gt;full
story
here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know what? It doesn't matter if you're working hard, put in your
hundred percent; but nothing seems to move at all. Hard work is never
wasted. One day or the other, you'll surely see the results. But they
would be reflected only when you 'put' in something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simply sitting back and relying on destiny to give you something isn't
and shouldn't be an option. You would only yield results when you put in
'efforts'.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please read that timeline given by Don Pinkus, how he improved, how he
worked upon his skills, how he never gave up and even resigned from his
job at Facebook to work on his project! That's certainly we should all
do! Follow our passion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Giving up should never be an option. Certain things might work for you;
certain might not. But it's very essential to keep on moving. And if you
follow your passion, actually do what you love, trust me, there would be
no looking back!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You would be always enjoying your work! Even 'master' was once a
'beginner'. So, how he became master now?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Answer is quite simple, by keep on working and never giving up! We
always have to start somewhere and at beginning we'll come up with
really terrible things, really bad ideas, work which would be 'trash' to
everyone else. But that's how you improve. Criticism should be always
taken as a positive thing. It should be something to help you in shaping
yourself. Improving upon yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing to remember:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A College Degree is important but so is common sense. The world is
full of Self-Taught Geniuses and Educated Fools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-Michael Baisden&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, there's no need to compare yourself with anyone, just try to
be a better person than what you were yesterday. Keep working hard and
never give up!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: For programmers, Don Pinkus have certain suggestions in his post,
you can read it!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2014 22:20:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2014-11-29:blog/be-inspired-keep-working-hard-never-give-up.html</guid><category>Inspiration</category></item><item><title>Time to wrap up the mess!</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/time-to-wrap-up-the-mess.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Finally got some time to write here. This one would be a really quick
post. I have been really busy from past few months. A hurricane of work
just kept me crunched every now and then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had to complete the summer training project report, write tutorial on my
own blog, submit dgplug training work (last task), learning about
bootstrap &amp;amp; complete some left freelancing work, then college work too.
I was literally trying to work with all that in parallel. So everything
seemed not to move at all. I apologize to everyone, trust me, I'm trying
my best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then came exams; damn, I hate it, they don't really test knowledge.They
are just there to know who has a damn 'Rattafication' skill. Anyways, my
exams got over yesterday. People in my class were a free bird, but it
isn't really an option for me at the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I just came back home and then carried out all the left tasks. Complete
two days work and finally I can see some output. My summer training
project report is now complete! And, and, and my reaction is like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="Summer Training Report completed in just 2 days" class="align-center" src="images/summer-training-report.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm happy as to 'something' is better than nothing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm just confused and crunched between a lot to do and at the moment
internals are again over my head. A lot of work is pending and I've to
complete it as soon as possible. A lot of college work too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time to work more aggressively and clear all the mess up! Plus, carry on
my college studies as well.&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 12 Nov 2014 00:11:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2014-11-12:blog/time-to-wrap-up-the-mess.html</guid></item><item><title>People: Why You NO Share Your Knowledge</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/people-why-you-no-share-your-knowledge.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;People are so much reluctant to share their knowledge. Like seriously?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The reasons they gave is, we spend money in getting it, why we
should give it for free?&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;img alt="Why you NO share your knowledge?" class="align-center" src="images/why_you_no_share_your_knowledge.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, can't believe why they do exist. If you don't want to share your
so called &amp;quot;Paid knowledge&amp;quot; for free, then how do you expect that others
teach you for free?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They spend tremendous hours just learning stuff they don't like, and
then ultimately asking for money to teach something they probably don't
know much good about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the event happened today in my class, when my linux faculty asked
suddenly from one person&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&amp;quot;What is Escape Sequence?&amp;quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and everyone was like&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&amp;quot;Ye kya hota hai?&amp;quot; (What is that?)&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suddenly people rushing here and there, and coming to me asking if I
knew. So I told them, but then also they acted like dumb. :(&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next the faculty started explaining that no one knew even about C or
C++, and then explained what is escape sequence. And I couldn't stop
laughing. Like seriously? People in my class claim they know C/C++ or
Java or even C# and they don't know what is escape sequence, still
rushing out the stuff they should probably know and what they want is a
&amp;quot;GOOD PAYING JOB&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I'm glad to tell, forget about a job, but first concentrate on
clearing your concepts. I'm not saying that I know things better than
you. I accept I'm still a noob, but at least I'm trying. I'm trying to
learn things which I like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you ask people&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&amp;quot;Why did you take Computer Science?&amp;quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;rather than technical questions which most of them just mug up, the
reactions you'll find are pretty much amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll see some dazzled faces around. Thinking what should they answer,
and that's the major issue here. People don't know why the heck they
opted for something they really don't like, moreover that they need to
have &lt;strong&gt;so much time&lt;/strong&gt; in just thinking about &amp;quot;Why they opted it?&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I always find it funny. People aren't really interested in Computer
Science, what they are really interested in is just getting a good job.
I'm trying to believe they'll get a good job, but why would someone
recruit a person who doesn't even know What he is doing in present,
forget about their future plannings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, the incident that pushed me to post on this topic, happened sometime
back in my class, when some students were offering to teach something to
other for money. They were so proud that they knew it ! Feeling like a
champ, they spent around 10k INR for that, so they asked other student
to pay 10k to them and they'll teach him.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WOW ! So cool, isn't it? But I'm astonished, how those so proud people
were not able to answer that simple question about escape sequence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not saying here that asking for money to give knowledge is bad. But
as a student you should help your peers, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if not, then let's say you fall into trouble and then say you rush
to someone and he asks money from you, even think everyone in the world
is asking money. Isn't that something really cruel? Isn't that something
you should not do in the first place itself, thinking you haven't really
achieved anything from that knowledge. What you know might be just half
that you were taught.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, get out of your ego to try to recover your money spend. Rather then
this, help people around you. You'll not only enjoy it, but it would
ultimately help you to clear your own concepts !&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Believe me, I don't know every damn thing, but when I try to clear
doubts of others ( about stuff which I think I know),&amp;nbsp; in this process I
might learn something important. Moreover it can happen, that I've
picked up a bad practice or I have some wrong information, so others can
correct that. It's like sharing your knowledge and getting it back ( A
two-way process)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not about teaching for free, it's about learning for free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Accept it, do it and feel the difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You're not professionals, first just focus on learning, it would help
you in the long run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: It's just your wish if you really want to take this &amp;quot;Free&amp;quot; advice or
still think your idea is better :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 13 Aug 2014 17:17:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2014-08-13:blog/people-why-you-no-share-your-knowledge.html</guid></item><item><title>It's getting hectic day by day</title><link>http://SanyamKhurana.com/blog/its-getting-hectic-day-by-day.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Glad that I took some time, to write here. My schedule is getting hectic
day by day. Only 4-5 hours sleep everyday. I'm tired, very tired but one
thing is going to happen sure shot. I'd like to die trying rather than
giving up :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My day starts with getting up [STRIKEOUT:early] late in morning around
7:45 AM and then preparing to [STRIKEOUT:go] rush to my college. It
takes approx 2 hours in commuting in just one way. So, in my whole day I
spend around 4 hours alone in traveling. Usual things happen in my
college, mostly [STRIKEOUT:studying] kind of wasting my time :(&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I liked that in this semester I would be studying really good
subjects about the Core Computer Science, but all my excitement was
drenched watching the pretty old syllabus. Never the less, I find some
topics really interesting in College too. Those about Algorithms and
DBMS are the best one out there. But I think Universities should focus
more on practical approach rather than just teaching students how to
[STRIKEOUT:learn]mug up things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The real learning curve begins when I reach home from college. Time is
really absurd and I reach around 7 PM in the evening or sometimes later
than that. I was regular in attending the DGPLUG classes, but this
schedule is seriously killing me. Never the less, I try to get on with
the logs if the class was there, or else I tend to do other things like
doing home task given in the previous class.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the research work about the articles I've to write begins. The
Geeky Way is facing a hard time now just because I take too much time to
update it, but I try to put up a good post (may be long) so as to
contribute some value rather than just focusing in increasing the post
count.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I take some time to do some freelancing work, I had already taken
(Now wouldn't take anymore for sometime). Among all these things, I find
myself standing awake in midnight. Usually, then I carry on with my
other courseware and practicing the things I've learned in my training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3 AM : Seriously?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes! It's generally 3 AM when I would sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though I usually don't find good resources to learn more, but when I do,
I ensure to make the full use of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not about learning to defeat someone, get a job or something. I
learn because I love to learn about that stuff, and I share my knowledge
because it's meant to be shared.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PS: Everyone has got 24 hours in a day, how you make use of it, is what
matters. If you tend to enjoy your whole day, and still wanting
something extra achieved, you won't. Because there's no short-cut to
success. You have to work hard for it. It's meant to be earned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now time to complete my home task for the training.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good Bye!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Sanyam Khurana</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 12 Aug 2014 22:21:00 +0530</pubDate><guid>tag:SanyamKhurana.com,2014-08-12:blog/its-getting-hectic-day-by-day.html</guid></item></channel></rss>